<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reply to an answer to the Defence of Amicia, daughter of Hugh Cyveliok, Earl of Chester wherein it is proved, that the reasons alleadged by Sir Peter Leicester, in his former book, and also in his said answer, concerning the illegitimacy of the said Amicia, are invalid, and of no weight at all / by Sir Thomas Mainwaring ...</title>
            <author>Mainwaring, Thomas, Sir, 1623-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51562</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10002</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13111352</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13111352</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97674</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51562)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97674)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 744:46)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reply to an answer to the Defence of Amicia, daughter of Hugh Cyveliok, Earl of Chester wherein it is proved, that the reasons alleadged by Sir Peter Leicester, in his former book, and also in his said answer, concerning the illegitimacy of the said Amicia, are invalid, and of no weight at all / by Sir Thomas Mainwaring ...</title>
                  <author>Mainwaring, Thomas, Sir, 1623-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 105 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for S. Lowndes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mainwaring, Amicia.</term>
               <term>Leycester, Peter, --  Sir, 1614-1678. --  Defence of Amicia.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97674:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97674:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REPLY TO AN ANSWER To the DEFENCE of AMICIA, Daughter of <hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GH CYVELIOK</hi> EARL of <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein it is Proved, That the <hi>REASONS</hi> Alleadged by <hi>Sir Peter Leiceſter.</hi> In his former <hi>Book,</hi> and alſo in his ſaid <hi>Anſwer,</hi> concerning the Illegitimacy of the ſaid <hi>Amicia,</hi> are invalid, and of no weight at all.</p>
            <p>By Sir <hi>Thomas Mainwating</hi> of <hi>Peover</hi> in <hi>CHESHIRE,</hi> Baronet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>S. Lowndes</hi> over againſt <hi>Exeter</hi>-Houſe in the <hi>Strand.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97674:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97674:2"/>
            <head>TO S<hi rend="sub">r</hi> PETER LEICESTER, <hi>BARONET.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Reaſons which you and I have alledged for and againſt <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> being now made publick, all Perſons may eaſily judge, whether, (as you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) it was onely the zeal of my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion touching her Legitimacy, which cauſed me to endeavor to incline the world to concur with me therein, or that what I ſaid was ſupported with juſt Grounds and Reaſons; and I doubt not but thoſe of our County that are underſtanding Perſons, will as eaſily diſcern from ſome of your omiſsions, (although I forbear pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly to take notice of them) that it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97674:3"/>was ſomething elſe beſides your great love to Truth (pretended by your alledging the old Rule of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi>) which occaſioned you thus to aſperſe your deceaſed Grandmother. But however things are, you have no reaſon to ſuſpect any animoſities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us, I having in my firſt Book (as I hope I ſhall alſo do in this) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to avoid all expreſſions, which I did conceive might be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, and I am confident you have no juſt cauſe to be angry with me, for endeavoring to defend a deceaſed Grandmother whom I ſuppoſe to be very much injur'd by you.</p>
            <p>I know not how far your memory may fail you therein, but I am ſure I have ſeveral times moved you (and particularly came once purpoſely to you to <hi>Tabley</hi>) to deſire that you would be contented to deliver what you did conceit concerning <hi>Amicia,</hi> as an uncertainty onely, (as you had done that of <hi>Roger,</hi> Son of <hi>Hugh Cyve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liok</hi>) and did at all thoſe times aſſure you that if you would ſo do, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, expreſs that ſome <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralds</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97674:3"/>were of a different judgement from you, that I would never trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you or the Reader with any Lines of mine. And the reaſon why I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired you thus to do, was, becauſe the Reader would certainly conclude <hi>Amicia</hi> to be a Baſtard, though no reaſons were alledged, if he ſaw one who was deſcended of her, to declare her illegitimate in Print, and did not know that ſome Learned Men were of a different opinion; but I could not poſſibly prevail with you herein. And although what you alledge be true, <hi>that there is no medium betwixt being a Bastard and Legitimate, but that a Man muſt abſolutely be the one or the other,</hi> yet, as to the Writer of an <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> the caſe may be different; for he may be certain, that ſome, concerning whom he writes, may be Legitimate, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may be Baſtards, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ought ſo to place them; but it is poſſible there may be ſome which he is uncertain, whether they be Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards or not; and in that caſe the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian ought to expreſs it doubtfully, and not to take upon him abſolutely to determine the point upon uncertain grounds.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97674:4"/>
            <p>As to your ſaying in the fourth page of your Anſwer, in the Margent, that <hi>you apprehend not why I call Sir</hi> Ralph Mainwaring, <hi>Chief Juſtice of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>when in thoſe Ages there was only one Judge at a time there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My reaſon wherefore I ſo did, was becauſe I found that <hi>Reginald Gray,</hi> who was Judge of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> had taken unto him as an Aſſociate, <hi>Ralph Hegham,</hi> in the thirteenth year of King <hi>Edward</hi> the I as appears page 172. of your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities:</hi> as alſo, becauſe I found in your ſaid Book, before the time of Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> two Deeds of <hi>Randle de Gernoniis,</hi> (which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to imply, that there had been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more Juſtices of <hi>Cheſter</hi> than one at a time,) the one of which as appears, page 128. was directed, <hi>Conſtabulario, Dapifero, Baronibus, J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STICIARIIS, &amp;c.</hi> and the other, as you may ſee, page 160. was directed, <hi>Epiſcopo Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriae, Dapifero, Baronibus, J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STICIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIIS, &amp;c.</hi> ſo that I hope, I am juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable herein.</p>
            <p>And though it was not uſual till af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ages, to have two Juſtices of <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97674:4"/>at one time, and that I have not yet found, that in the time of <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> there was any Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> but the ſaid <hi>Ralph,</hi> yet it being poſſible for the reaſons aforeſaid, that there might be more than one at a time; I did therefore call the ſaid <hi>Ralph,</hi> Chief Juſtice, to ſhew if there were then two, that he was the chief of them, becauſe he acted as Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter</hi> alone, as will thus appear from a Roll of antient Charts, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Doomesday,</hi> remaining in the Caſtle of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> amongſt the Records there.</p>
            <q>Leuca quae fuit uxor Ranulphi de Kingeſleigh veniens in pleno Com. Ceſtriae coram Radulpho de Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring tunc Juſticiario Ceſtriae &amp; Baronibus, &amp;c. quiet. clam. Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chardo de Kingeſleigh totam villant de Bertherton unde dotata fuit.</q>
            <p>And whereas you pretend page 4 and 5. of your Anſwer, (which is the onely example which you bring to prove what you there alledge) that <hi>Geffrey de Dutton,</hi> who made the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Deed of <hi>Nether-Tabley</hi> had this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97674:5"/>word <hi>Domino,</hi> ſometimes prefixed to his Name, when he was a Witneſs, and yet was no Knight; and thence would inferre, that the word <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> is no ſure rule, to be always under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of a Knight. I ſhall before I give an anſwer unto what you ſay, tranſcribe the ſaid Deed out of your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities,</hi> as I find it in the 355 page of your ſaid Book.</p>
            <q>Sciant praeſentes &amp; futuri, quod ego Galfridus de Dutton dedi &amp; conceſſi &amp; hac praeſenti Charta mea confirmavi Margaretae ſiliae meae, pro homagio &amp; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitio ſuo totam villam meam, quae vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur Parva-Tabley, ſine ullo retenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, cum Homagiis &amp; Servitiis, cum Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenagiis, cum Boſcis, cum Planis, cum Pratis, &amp; Paſcuis, cum Moris &amp; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſcis, cum Aquis &amp; Molendinis, cum Viis &amp; Semitis, cum omnibus locis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictae Villae pertinentibus: Tenendam &amp; habendam ſibi Margaretae, &amp; Haeredibus ſuis, de me Galfrido, &amp; Haeredibus meis, liberè quiete, &amp; paciſicè, cum omnibus li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertatibus, &amp; Ayſiamentis praedictae villae pertinentibus: Faciendo inde mihiforin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecum ſervitium, quantum pertinet ad
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97674:5"/>duas Bovatas terrae,, unde trigint a Bova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae Terrae faciunt Feodum unius Militis, &amp; faciendo ſervitium de <hi>Hauthoner</hi> quantum pertinet ad praedictam villam, pro omni ſeculari ſervitio, conſuetudine, &amp; demanda, mihi &amp; Haeredibus meis perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nente. Et ego Galfridus &amp; Haeredes mei prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictam villam, ut praedictum eſt, praedictae Margaretae &amp; haered. ſuis, contra omnes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines &amp; faeminas in perpetuum warranti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabimus Et ad majorem hujus rei ſecurita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem huic praeſenti ſcripto Sigillum appoſui meum. Hiis Teſtibus, Domino Thoma de Dutton, Domino Galfrido de Dutton, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone de Lymme, Thoma fratre ejus, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardo de Aſton, Rogero de Toft, Willielmo de Waleton, &amp; multis aliis.</q>
            <p>Now this <hi>Geffrey de Dutton,</hi> being that perſon who did give <hi>Little-Tabley,</hi> (now called <hi>Nether-Tabley,</hi> and the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Seat of your Family) unto <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> his Daughter and Heir, who firſt was married to <hi>Robert de Denbigh,</hi> and afterwards to Sir <hi>Nicholas Leiceſter,</hi> and ſo brought <hi>Nether-Tabley</hi> unto the <hi>Leiceſters;</hi> A Man would think that you ſhould be very well acquainted with all the Deeds that the ſaid <hi>Geffrey</hi> made, which are in your cuſtody, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97674:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>et I doubt not but to make it appear, that you have run into ſeveral very groſs errors, concerning that <hi>Geffrey de Dutton,</hi> who made the ſaid Deed; For firſt, page 4 and 5. of your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, you tell us (which is but your own fancy) that the word <hi>Dominus was applied to the better ſort of Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in thoſe ages who were no Knights, and that in thoſe elder Ages it was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times prefixed, and oftner omitted even to the ſame Men; as Domino Galfrido de Dutton, who in the Original Chart of</hi> Nether-Tabley <hi>writes himſelf only—Ego</hi> Galfridus <hi>de</hi> Dutton <hi>dedi, &amp;c. and ſeveral other Deeds you have ſeen of the ſame perſon (who you ſay was lineal Anceſtor to</hi> Warburton <hi>of</hi> Arley) <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you dare affirm among the Witneſſes ſubſcribed, he hath five times and more the word</hi> Dominus <hi>omitted, for once that we find it prefixed to his name; and you are very confident, was not in him, as many others alſo, to be conſtrued any more then Maſter</hi> Geffrey Dutton, <hi>and that he was no Knight;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To anſwer which, I ſhall thus far agree with you, That I believe the ſaid
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97674:6"/>
               <hi>Geffrey Dutton</hi> (Son of <hi>Geffrey,</hi> Son of <hi>Adam</hi>) who made the ſaid Deed of <hi>Little or Nether Tabley</hi> was no Knight, But I cannot imagine how it is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that the ſaid <hi>Geffrey de Dutton</hi> to that or any other Deeds of his own, could have his Name either with the word <hi>domino,</hi> or without, either five times for once, or at all, amongſt the witneſſes ſubſcribed, unleſs you fancy, that he was a Witneſs to his own Deeds, which is as groſs a thing as I have known; But beſides this, you run into another errour, and when you do indeed find the word <hi>dominus</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed to the name of <hi>Geffrey de Dutton</hi> as a Witneſs to other Mens Deeds, you will needs have that <hi>Dominus Galfridus de Dutton</hi> to be him, who made the ſaid Deed of <hi>Nether Tabley,</hi> whereas it was not he, but his Father, as I ſhall preſently make very manifeſt; For it is clear that you have ſeen no deed made by any <hi>Geffrey de Dutton,</hi> in which the word <hi>dominus</hi> is uſed by the party himſelf, becauſe, you tell us <hi>p.</hi> 5 <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. (but erroneouſly alſo, as will anon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear) that the word <hi>dominus</hi> is never uſed in old Deeds by the party himſelf,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97674:7"/>but where it is joyned with another word, as <hi>Ego Willielmus Manwaring Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus de Pever, Ego Robertus dominus Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aldiae;</hi> and alſo, <hi>p.</hi> 5. you onely ſpeak of his Name being ſubſcribed as a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo that all the Proof which you have of a <hi>Dominus Galfridus de Dutton</hi> is from his being called ſo by other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in other Mens Deeds: Now, it appearing in your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities, page</hi> 250. that <hi>Hugh de Dutton,</hi> Son of <hi>Hugh,</hi> Son of <hi>Hodard,</hi> had a ſecond Son named <hi>Adam de Dutton,</hi> (from whom you ſay the <hi>Warburtons</hi> of <hi>Arley</hi> are deſcended) and the ſaid <hi>Adam de Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> as appears in your ſaid Book, <hi>page</hi> 384. having iſſue a Son owned by you to be Sir <hi>Geffrey Dutton,</hi> which Sir <hi>Gef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey,</hi> as you confeſs, <hi>page</hi> 354 &amp; 355. had iſſue <hi>Geffrey Dutton,</hi> who made the ſaid Deed of <hi>Tabley,</hi> the ſaid Sir <hi>Gef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey Dutton</hi> the Father being then li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and a Witneſs to the ſaid Deed, you when you find a <hi>Dominus Galfri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus de Dutton</hi> to be a Witneſs to any Deed, will not own it (as you ought to do) to be Sir <hi>Geffrey Dutton</hi> Son of <hi>Adam,</hi> who indeed was a Knight, but you will have it to be <hi>Geffrey Dutton</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97674:7"/>the Grandſon of <hi>Adam,</hi> who was no Knight; But though perhaps you may by ſuch deviſes as theſe, impoſe upon ſome ſilly Readers, yet certainly no intelligent perſon will believe what you ſay concerning the ſame.</p>
            <p>Alſo, I might here ask you, whether the word <hi>Dominus</hi> when it is prefixed to the name of a perſon, who is not a Clergyman, doth prove him certainly to be a Knight, or not? If it do, Why will not you call every Layman a Knight, that hath it ſo prefixed? and if it do not, Why do you in your <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical Antiquities p.</hi> 330. &amp; 332. own Sir <hi>Thomas Mainwaring</hi> of <hi>Warmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cham,</hi> upon the like proof, to be a Knight? And Why (as appears in the 8 <hi>Page</hi> of your <hi>Anſwer</hi> to my <hi>Defence</hi> of <hi>Amicia</hi>) <hi>did you fully intend to have called</hi> Ralph Mainwaring, Roger Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring <hi>and</hi> William Mainwaring, <hi>all Knights, but that you know not by what fate it was forgotten?</hi> And, Why do you all along in your later Book ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them to be Knights?</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>p.</hi> 5 <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. that, <hi>the word</hi> Dominus <hi>is never uſed in old Deeds, by the party himſelf, but when it is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97674:8"/>joyned with another word, as</hi> Ego Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmus Mainwaring Dominus de Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Ego Robertus Dominus Moaldiae, <hi>but is only uſed when the party is ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed as a witneſs;</hi> Though that be true for the moſt part, yet it doth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes hold, as will appear by two Deeds of Sir <hi>Thomas Mainwarings</hi> of <hi>Warmincham,</hi> which I have by me, ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with two Barres in Green-wax, written about thus, <hi>S. Tome le Mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warig;</hi> which Deeds you have ſeen, and are as followeth;</p>
            <q>
               <p>Sciant praeſentes &amp; futuri quod ego Dominus <hi>Thomas</hi> de Menylgaring dedi conceſſi &amp; hac praeſenti carta mea confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mavi Hamoni filio <hi>Johannis</hi> de <hi>Bruerio</hi> pro homagio &amp; ſervitio ſuo quinque acras terrae in Villa de Cogiſhull, illas, ſcilicet, quas de me prius tenuit ad terminum, cum aumento perficiendi quinque acras inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gras ſine impedimento, &amp; ſicut ſepe foſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſato metis &amp; bundis circueuntur &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentur, &amp; cum omnibus aliis pertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis ſuis, &amp; pro tribus marcis &amp; dimid. argenti, quas mihi dedit praemani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus: Habendum &amp; tenendum de dicto <hi>Domino Thoma</hi> &amp; haeredibus ſuis, dicto Hamoni &amp; haeredibus ſuis &amp; aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natis,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97674:8"/>libere, quiete, integre, haereditarie, imperpetuum, in boſco, in plano, in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, in paſcuis, in viis, in ſemitis, in aquis, in moris, in omnibus communibus, &amp; aſyamentis Villae de Cokiſhull ubique pertinentibus: Reddendo inde annua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim dicto <hi>Domino Thome</hi> &amp; haeredibus ſuis duos ſolidos &amp; ſex denarios ad duos anni terminos, videlicet, ad Nativita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Sancti <hi>Johannis Baptiſtae</hi> quinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem denarios, &amp; ad festum Sancti <hi>Martini</hi> in yeme quindecem denarios pro omni ſervitio ſeculari, exactione &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manda mihi &amp; haeredibus meis pertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus: Et ego vero dictus <hi>Dominus Thomas</hi> &amp; haeredes mei dicto Hamoni &amp; haeredibus ſuis &amp; aſſignatis totas prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict as quinque acras terrae cum omnibus pertinentiis ſuis ſicut praenotatum eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra omnes homines &amp; foeminas waran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizabimus &amp; defendemus imperpetuum. In hujus rei teſtimonium huic praeſenti carta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſigillum meum appoſui, Hiis Teſtibus, <hi>Hugone</hi> de <hi>Duram, Willielmo Bernard</hi> tunc Seneſchallo domini <hi>Thomae</hi> de <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nylgaring, Richardo Starkye, Rober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> de <hi>Wynninton, Ranulpho</hi> de <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorton, Thoma</hi> de Queloc, <hi>Johanne</hi> de <hi>Merbury, Rogero</hi> clerico, &amp; aliis.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97674:9"/>
               <p>Sciant praeſentes &amp; futuri quod ego Dominus <hi>Thomas</hi> de <hi>Menylgaring</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di conceſſi &amp; hac praeſenti carta mea confirmavi <hi>Roberto</hi> de <hi>Bexeckne</hi> pro homagio &amp; ſervitio totam illam terram quam mercatus fuit de <hi>Hugone</hi> de <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deney</hi> ſicut ſepe &amp; foſſato circuitur &amp; includitur &amp; metis &amp; bundis continetur cum omnibus pertinentiis ſuis: Haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum &amp; tenendum de me &amp; haeredibus meis &amp; aſſignatis dicto <hi>Roberto</hi> &amp; hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redibus ſuis &amp; aſſignatis, libere, quiete, integre, haereditarie, in pace, bene, in boſco, in plano, in aquis, in viis, in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitis, in pratis, in paſturis, cum hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bold &amp; haybold, &amp; tacfre, de omnibus propriis porcis ſuis infra omnes metas de Cokiſhull, &amp; cum omnibus aliis commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus &amp; eſyamentis praedictae villae ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantibus: Reddendo inde annuatim mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi &amp; haeredibus meis &amp; meis aſsignatis quindecem denarios argenti ad duos anni terminos, videlicet ad nativitatem ſancti <hi>Johannis</hi> Baptiſtae ſeptem denari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os &amp; obolum &amp; ad feſtum ſancti Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni in yeme ſeptem denarios &amp; obolum pro omnibus ſervitiis ſecularibus exactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus &amp; demandis praedictae terrae per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentibus:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97674:9"/>Et ego vero <hi>Dominus Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> de Menilgaring &amp; haeredes mei &amp; aſſignati mei dicto Roberto &amp; haeredibus ſuis &amp; aſſignatis totam praedictam ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram ſicut ſepe &amp; foſſato circuitur &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluditur, &amp; ſicut proenotatum eſt contra omnes homines &amp; faeminas imperpetuum warrantizabimus &amp; defendemus: Pro hac autem donatione conceſsione &amp; car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae meae confirmatione dedit mihi dictus Robertus quatuor ſolidos argenti praema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus: In cujus rei teſtimonium huic praeſenti cartae ſigillum meum appoſui: Hiis teſtibus, Richardo Starkey, Williel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Bernard tunc Seneſchallo Domini Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae de Menilgaring, Johanne de Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, Hugone de eadem, Hugone ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio Hamonis de Comberbach, Ad. de Acton, Roberto de Burwys, Rogero Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rico, &amp; aliis.</p>
            </q>
            <p>And as to what you ſay, page 8. of your <hi>Anſwer, that as the word</hi> Sir, <hi>is in common diſcourſe applicable to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of quality from the higheſt to the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in its larger notion, ſo</hi> Dominus <hi>is applicable to any Knight or Gentleman, as if you ſhould ſay, Domine quaeſo, num hoc verum eſt quod dieo, neene?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97674:10"/>
            <p>I grant it to be true, but then as you obſerve, the word <hi>Sir,</hi> or the word <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus</hi> muſt onely ſo be taken in its <hi>larger notion,</hi> but that is ſo far from weakening what I ſay, that it doth confirm it; For though if I ſpeak to one whoſe name is <hi>Peter,</hi> that is but a Gentleman, I may properly uſe the word <hi>Sir</hi> to him, yet I cannot proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly joyn the word <hi>Sir</hi> to his name, and call him <hi>Sir Peter,</hi> unleſs the ſaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be either a Baronet or a Knight, and that is the caſe in theſe old Deeds, where the word <hi>Dominus</hi> is prefixed to the names of the ſaid Knights.</p>
            <p>Alſo, if the word <hi>Dominus</hi> do only ſignify <hi>Maſter,</hi> (as you would have it) What is the reaſon, that in ſome Deeds it is only put before the names of ſome of the witneſſes, and not before the names of others? although thoſe other perſons to whoſe names it is not put, many times are Lords of ſeveral Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, and perſons of very great Eſtate.</p>
            <p>As to what you alledge, page 6. of your <hi>Arſwer to my defence of</hi> Amicia,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97674:10"/>that in the 27 page of my ſaid <hi>Defence,</hi> Radulfus <hi>de</hi> Meidnilwaring <hi>after his Daughter</hi> Bertrey <hi>was marriageable is there named without his Title of</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus; You your ſelf have anſwered that a little before, by confeſſing (though the word <hi>Domino</hi> is uſually ſet to the name of ſuch a perſon when he is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a witneſs) that the word <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> is never uſed by the party himſelf, but where it is joyned with another word, as <hi>Ego Willielmus Mainwaring Dominus de Peover, Ego Rogerus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus Moaldiae,</hi> which though for the moſt part it be very true, yet I have ſhewed that it doth not ever hold; But inſtead of obſerving that you had given a full anſwer to this objection of your own, you ſtrangely fancy, that I would poſſibly ſay, that that Deed was made before the ſaid <hi>Ralph</hi> was Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter;</hi> whereas in the 74 page of my ſaid Book, I had told you, that the ſaid Deed was ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made before the ſaid <hi>Ralph</hi> was Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> that it was made after he had parted with the ſaid Office; And thus you became guilty of a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble levity, firſt, in making an objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97674:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>which you your ſelf had anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but in the preceding page, and then in framing an anſwer thereto for me, directly contrary to what I had formerly ſaid.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, page 8. that <hi>you had rather give to any, eſpecially to my Family, more then is due, then leſs;</hi> I could wiſh I had juſt cauſe to be of that opinion; For I am ſure you have omitted in our Deſcent, not only <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulfus,</hi> who is nominated in <hi>Doomes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day Book,</hi> but alſo <hi>Richard Meſnilwaren</hi> mentioned in your <hi>Hiſtorical Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, pag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Roger de Menilgarin,</hi> and
<note n="*" place="margin">Note. <hi>That page.</hi> 117. <hi>of your</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>you have pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced</hi> Randle <hi>before</hi> William, <hi>contrary to what you have done Pa.</hi> 341. <hi>and contrary to</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſticon Anglica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. Par. 1. Pa. 985.</note> 
               <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Randle</hi> his Sons, ſpoken of by you page 341. <hi>Roger de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nilgarin</hi> or <hi>Mainwaring,</hi> named by you page 362. Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> and Sir <hi>Roger Mainwaring</hi> his Son, both taken notice of by you pa. 330. and this upon a pretence, that they were Lords of <hi>Warmincham,</hi> whereas I am confident you will not deny but that the <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warings</hi> of <hi>Warmincham</hi> were alſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97674:11"/>owners of <hi>Over-Peover</hi> or the moſt part thereof, until Sir <hi>Roger Mainwaring</hi> gave <hi>Peover</hi> to his younger Son Sir <hi>William Mainwaring,</hi> and it was not long after, that the <hi>Mainwarings</hi> of <hi>Peover</hi> became Heirs male to thoſe <hi>Mainwarings</hi> of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mincham,</hi> Sir <hi>Warine Mainwaring,</hi> Son of Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> Son of the ſaid Sir <hi>Roger,</hi> dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without iſſue Male; Alſo I am ſure you denyed to do us right in one other particular, when you did it in the like caſe for another Family, which had not ſo clear proof for it as mine had.</p>
            <p>As for your new quarrel, (page 9 of your Anſwer) with the Herald, for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to Sir <hi>Randle Mainwaring</hi> my great Grandfather ſix <hi>Barrulets,</hi> as his moſt proper Coat, whereas you ſay, <hi>ever ſince the time of</hi> Sir <hi>Roger Mainwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, aſwell the Heirs of the right Line, as alſo the</hi> Mainwarings <hi>of</hi> Peover <hi>(after they became next Heirs Male) have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly born the two barres, for ſome hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of years;</hi> I might reply and tell you, that the <hi>Mainwarings,</hi> of <hi>Peover</hi> have not conſtantly given, <hi>Argent,</hi> two <hi>Barres Gules,</hi> ſince they became Heirs Male to the <hi>Mainwarings</hi> of <hi>Warmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cham,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:97674:12"/>as appears by my Deeds; Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I think that Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> did look upon the <hi>Six Barrulets,</hi> as a Coat moſt peculiar to us; for, in his <hi>Britannia</hi> in his Deſcription of the County of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> he names the <hi>two Barres</hi> as the Coat moſt proper to our Family, as appears by theſe words of his, when he writes of <hi>Aſtbury Church, viz. Haec enim perpulchra eſt, cujus porticus Occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentalis ipſam Eccleſiam, quae ſane alta, ſua altitudine adaequat, &amp; pyramidem ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctam habet. In caemeterio duae jacent ſepulchrales Militum effigies, in quorum ſcutis ſunt duae directae areolae ſive Barrae. Verum cum coloribus ſuis deſtituantur non facile quis dixerit fuerintne ex</hi> Brereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, <hi>Mainwaringis, vel de</hi> Venables, <hi>quae clariſsimae ſunt in vicinia familiae, &amp; ejuſmodi</hi> Barras <hi>variantibus coloribus gentilitiis in clypeis geſtant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I rather think that my Great Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father having a Fancy to that Coat of <hi>Six Barrulets</hi> more than to that of the <hi>two Barres,</hi> becauſe the moſt antient of our Deeds were ſealed therewith, that Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> gave him liberty to bear either the one or the other, which I
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97674:12"/>ſee not but it might be done, being our Family had for ſeveral generations uſually born the one, and the other had been born by our Anceſtor, and had never been uſed by any other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and I am ſure, though you be ſo captious with us, that you your ſelf have of late years given a different Creſt, from what had for a long time been born by your Predeceſſors, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you found a more antient Creſt in ſome of your Seals: And whereas you inſtance <hi>in the great Suit, betwixt</hi> Scroop <hi>and</hi> Groſvenour <hi>in the Marſhals Court, under</hi> Richard <hi>the</hi> II. <hi>concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bearing of a Coat of Arms, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to both challenged a right and propriety by uſage, but no other way;</hi> You thence rightly infer, that uſage makes a right in ſuch caſes; but when you ſay, that <hi>uſage only makes a right;</hi> you are miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken therein, For (not to mention the caſe in hand, where a mans Anceſtor hath born a Coat, which for ſometime hath been laid aſide, but never taken up by any other Family) a Man could then have no right to a Coat, which was given him by a King of Arms.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97674:13"/>
            <p>I am ſtill of opinion, that you have branded ſeveral perſons in your Book with Baſtardy, without any proof thereof, but ſhall not yet concern my ſelf for any (beſides my own Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor) except ſuch as you give me juſt occaſion to take notice of; And as for <hi>Geva</hi> and <hi>Richard Bacun's</hi> Mother, the firſt of them is not yet by you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be a Baſtard, and I ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly hereafter make it appear, that the ſecond was no Daughter of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> ſo that <hi>Amicia</hi> is like to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no <hi>blow</hi> at all; And if they were both Baſtards, it would be no preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to <hi>Amicia,</hi> becauſe I have in my former Book fully proved, that the gift to <hi>Geva</hi> was not a Gift in <hi>Free-Marriage,</hi> (as that to <hi>Amicia</hi> was) and you do not pretend at all, that any ſuch gift was made to the Mother of <hi>Richard Bacun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas you tell me <hi>you believe that</hi> Geva <hi>and the wife of</hi> Bacun <hi>had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been ſpoken of, nor ſuſpected, nor doubted of by me, had not the caſe of</hi> Amicia <hi>been concerned</hi> I can aſſure you
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97674:13"/>I ſhould have been of the ſame opinion concerning them, if you had never mentioned <hi>Amicia;</hi> but if you had not pretended from their Caſes, to raiſe ſome Arguments againſt the ſaid <hi>Amicia,</hi> I ſhould never have troubled my ſelf about them, and therefore I forbear to tell you of all miſtakes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſuch as the caſe in hand doth give me juſt occaſion to obſerve. And whereas you ſay, page 12. that <hi>you think you ſhall make good what you have alledged, with as much certainty as the nature of the thing and times will admit.</hi> And alſo page 27. that <hi>Geva</hi> was <hi>certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Baſtard, by as good proof us can poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be expected in ſuch a caſe;</hi> You do thereby implicitely confeſs, that you do not make thoſe things appear with any certainty at all.</p>
            <p>I have now done with what you have ſaid concerning my <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> and ſhall now proceed to conſider of your <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the Book it ſelf; and becauſe you do in ſeveral places, again ſay, what you have ſaid heretofore, I hope the Reader will excuſe me, if I be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained ſometimes to repeat the ſame
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97674:14"/>things, which I alſo have formerly ſaid.</p>
            <p>In the 14 and 15 pages, you do tell me that I ſaid I would remind you of that which you had formerly been told, <hi>viz.</hi> Who thoſe <hi>Heralds</hi> were that gave to <hi>Mainwaring</hi> of <hi>Peover</hi> the quartering of the Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi>'s Coat, in Queen <hi>Eliſabeth's</hi> time, and withal do ſay, that <hi>I never told you, till long time after that part of your Book was written,</hi> which, perhaps may be true, becauſe that part of your Book was written very long ſince, <hi>viz.</hi> in the year 1647. but I am ſure I have often told you of them, and you have alſo often ſeen the <hi>Pedigree</hi> it ſelf, under the hands of Mr. <hi>Cambden,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sampſon Erdeſwick;</hi> the reſt in that place is only the repeating of your former quarrel with them, for ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to quarter the Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi>'s Coat, but if we can really prove, that we are of the Half Blood, whatever you conceive of it, I ſuppoſe all indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent perſons will think it but meet, that we ſhould have the like liberty that all others have in the like caſe, in theſe laſt ages of ours.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:97674:14"/>
            <p>What you ſay in the 16 and 17 pages, hath been ſome of it formerly ſaid in your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities,</hi> and alſo in the 15 page of this your <hi>Anſwer,</hi> and there is nothing there that is new, but that you only alledge, that <hi>as to my note of Dukes and Earls to have been antiently Judges of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>I ſhould have diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed the times, for that was not till the Reign of</hi> Richard <hi>the</hi> II. <hi>(who made Deputies to act in their ſtead) before which time there were no ſuch great perſons Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es there, nor from</hi> Henry <hi>the Sevenths time downwards;</hi> But what neceſſity there was for me particularly to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh the times in which thoſe great Dukes and Earls were Judges of <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> I do not know; For I only inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in that to ſhew, that the place of <hi>Judge of Cheſter</hi> was antiently a place of great repute, and though it was ſome time after the death of <hi>John Scot,</hi> before any ſuch great perſons were made Judges of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> by the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and that in all the times of the Earls of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> before that Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was united to the Crown, there could not be any Dukes or Earls made
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97674:15"/>Judges there, becauſe there were no ſuch perſons belonging to the then Earls, (except <hi>John Lacy</hi> Conſtable of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> who was not made Earl of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> as appears in your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities</hi> page 270. till the 23 of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> 1232. which was but four years and upwards before the death of <hi>John Scot</hi> the laſt of the ſaid Earls) yet there were ever antiently perſons of good quality that were Judges of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and if it had not been always a place of great repute, the Kings of <hi>England</hi> would never have made ſuch very great perſons to have ſucceeded them therein.</p>
            <p>As to what you alledge in the 18, 19, 20, and 21 pages of your <hi>Anſwer,</hi> I do not doubt (though you affirm it can never be proved) but that I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in my former Book, given moſt perſons ſatisfaction, that <hi>Amicia</hi> was of the Half-Blood to Earl <hi>Randle,</hi> by a former wife of Earl <hi>Hugh;</hi> And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you object, that it is more rational to imagine, that <hi>Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>matching his only Daughter, which he had by a former Wife, would have married her to as conſiderable a perſon as was either pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97674:15"/>by himſelf, or his Son for his young<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er Children by a ſecond venter;</hi> I do an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer and ſay, That I am not certain whether <hi>Amicia</hi> was the only Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had by his former Wife; becauſe, I know ſome that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend they can tell of ſome other Daughter or Daughters which the ſaid Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had by his ſaid Wife; but I do confeſs, I have never ſeen juſt proof of any but her; but ſuppoſing her to be the only Child by his firſt Wife; I have in my former Book, pa. 23, 24, and 25. ſhewed that there is no ſtrength in this Argument of yours; And I may here further add, that if you will ſearch for examples, you may find very many, where the elder Siſters, ſometimes, becauſe ſwayed by their affections, and ſometimes for other reaſons, have not been married to ſo great perſons as the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Siſters have been; neither can you tell what portions Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> gave to <hi>Amicia,</hi> or to any of his other Daughters: neither is there any neceſſity that the elder Siſter, becauſe by a former wife, muſt have as great a portion as a younger Siſter by a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97674:16"/>latter Wife; becauſe, many times per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are not able to give ſo great porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in their younger days, as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: and becauſe, the Children of the living Wife are oftentimes better provided for, than thoſe of the dead Wife; and of this, I could if I pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, inſtance in ſome that I know; and in caſe the Father dye, and leave one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iſſue Female by a firſt, and a Son and iſſue Female by a latter wife (as in this caſe) there is great likelihood (beſides the advantage that the Siſters by the latter wife would have by being Heirs at Law to their Brother, he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without iſſue) that the Brother will naturally be more kind to thoſe Siſters that are of the Whole-Blood, and about the ſame age, and bred up with him, than he will be to her that is but his Half-Siſter, and much older then himſelf.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, pa. 18, and 19. that <hi>the expectation of Earl</hi> Randle Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devile's <hi>Siſters of the Whole Blood (which I conceive added to their fortunes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they matched to ſo great perſons) could not be much, being grounded upon great
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97674:16"/>uncertainties, ſince it could not be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen (when they married) that their Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould dye without iſſue, who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards married two wives ſucceſsively, purpoſely to have iſſue of his own Body, to inherit his own Lands;</hi> I do think if you conſider it, you cannot in good earneſt believe, that the ſaid Earl <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Blundevil</hi>'s four Siſters were marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the ſaid Earl married his firſt wife, whatever they were when he married his ſecond wife; For, <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred</hi> the Mother of <hi>Randle Blundevil</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aged but twenty four years when her Husband Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> died, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, <hi>Rot. de Dominabus pueris, &amp;c. in Scacc. penes remem. R. ſub Tit. Linc. Rot.</hi> 1. and the ſaid <hi>Randle,</hi> as appears in your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities,</hi> page 146. being married to <hi>Conſtance</hi> the Widow of <hi>Geffrey,</hi> fourth Son of King <hi>Henry</hi> the II. and Daughter and Heir of <hi>Conan</hi> Duke of little <hi>Brittain,</hi> and Earl of <hi>Richmond,</hi> in the year 1187. at which time the ſaid <hi>Bertred</hi> was but about Thirty years old; Can any one think that all the five Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the ſaid <hi>Bertred</hi> were then mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried?</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:97674:17"/>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, that it was I who informed you of the three eminent Judges, and four Heralds that were of opinion, that <hi>Amicia</hi> was Legitimate: If your meaning be, that I was the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſon who informed you thereof, I muſt impute it to the weakneſs of your memory, which fails you in this particular; For, you had many times ſeen our <hi>Pedigree,</hi> atteſted by Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sampſon Erdeſwick,</hi> who did allow her to be a <hi>Legitimate</hi> Daughter, and ſeveral years ſince, two other Heralds, who are yet living, at <hi>Cheſter</hi> did declare to you in my hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that ſhe could not be a Baſtard, and the one of them then named to you a <hi>Chief Juſtice</hi> of the <hi>Common Pleas,</hi> and a <hi>Lord Keeper</hi> of the Great Seal of <hi>England</hi> (both now deceaſed) who did concur with them therein, and you have alſo ſeen an opinion of a Third, Judge under his Hand, together, with Reaſons for the ſame; and though you ſpeak ſo ſlightly of the opinions of Judges and Heralds, <hi>in comparing them to Hands got to a Petition or Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate, and pretend it was without hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97674:17"/>the Reaſons on the other ſide;</hi> I very well know (though it ſeems you have forgotten it) that that hand which was obtained, was procured, becauſe you ſeemed to deſire to know his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion in the caſe; And I alſo know that thoſe two Heralds, who at <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> did declare their judgements a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, did then hear all the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that you could then alledge.</p>
            <p>As to what you ſay, pa. 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, and part of the 27, in all which you would willingly prove, that the Common-Law is now altered ſome other way than by Statute, you do but loſe your labor, and can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver prove the ſame; For, in that <hi>Maxime</hi> of the Law, where it is ſaid, That <hi>whatſoever was at the Common-Law, and is not ouſted or taken away by any Statute, remaineth ſtill;</hi> the words <hi>ouſted</hi> or <hi>taken away,</hi> muſt needs be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken conjunctively, and muſt neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bear this ſence, <hi>that the Common-Law ſtill is the ſame in all points, as it was before, except where taken away by Statute;</hi> and if thoſe words ſhould be taken otherwiſe, then, the meaning
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97674:18"/>would be this, <hi>that that part of the Common-Law which doth remain, doth remain,</hi> which would be a very ſtrange <hi>Maxime;</hi> And whereas you hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore urged ſome places, to prove, that the Common-Law is alter'd at this day from what it was in former ages, long after the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the II. which you now alſo urge again in the 24 page of your latter Book; I muſt give you the ſame anſwer which I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly did, <hi>viz.</hi> That thoſe places do not prove that the Common-Law at this day doth vary from what it was in former ages, in any particular, but onely that it was taken to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in thoſe days, and that it was but juſt like ſome Caſes in our <hi>Reports,</hi> which have at ſeveral times been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged directly contrary to each other; but notwithſtanding that, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law was ſtill the ſame; And that I might come as near you as I could; I did then acknowledge that though the Common-Law was ever the ſame, where not alter'd by Parliament: yet in former ages, they did in ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, take the Law to be otherways than they now do; And I did alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97674:18"/>that if you could prove, that they had done ſo formerly in this caſe of <hi>Frank-Marriage,</hi> that it would have taken off much of the ſtrength of my Argument from the words <hi>in libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro Maritagio,</hi> becauſe, that antient Deeds and Grants (according to what my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> on <hi>Littleton</hi> ſays, fol 8. b. at the bottom) are to be expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the Law was taken to be at the time of the Grant: Now theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which you alledge, do not prove a change of the Common-Law, in any particular, other than by Statute, but only that the Law was ſometimes dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently taken in one Age, from what it was in another Age; for in your 24 page, where you cite <hi>Coke upon Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleton, fol.</hi> 34. <hi>Sect.</hi> 39. you do not there ſay, that my Lord <hi>Coke</hi>'s words were, That the Law was different in <hi>Glanvile</hi>'s time in the particular you there mention, from what it is now; but you ſay, that he ſaith that in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient times, as it appears by <hi>Glanvile, lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>it was taken</hi> (that is, the Law was taken) <hi>that a Man could not have endowed his Wife, ad Oſtium Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae, of more than a third part, but of leſs
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97674:19"/>he might: but at this day the Law is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,</hi> (as <hi>Littleton</hi> holdeth, <hi>which is</hi>) <hi>That a Man may Endow his Wife</hi> ad Oſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Eccleſiae <hi>of his whole Land, or of the half, or other leſs part,</hi> which is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame thing that I ſaid; And where you again cite <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Littleton,</hi> fol. 8. a. towards the bottom, you bring him in, ſaying, that <hi>of antient time the Heir was permitted to have an action of Debt upon a Bond made to his Anceſtor and his Heir, but the Law is not ſo at this day;</hi> but my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> doth not ſay as you do, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Law is not ſo at this day, but that the Law is not ſo <hi>holden</hi> at this day; ſo that he ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voids the expreſſion of <hi>the Law being changed.</hi> (otherways than by Statute) although it was differently holden in ſeveral Ages; And thus, as you may ſee <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Littleton,</hi> fol. 21. b. in the Caſe of <hi>Piers de Saltmarſh</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, it was judged in King <hi>Edward</hi> the Thirds time, and in King <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourths time, That a Man might give Land to his Son in Frankmarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, but in King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighths time, it was holden otherways, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Books being not remembred; But
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97674:19"/>notwithſtanding, that this point was judged thus differently, the Law was ſtill the ſame and all that can be ſaid, is, that ſome of the judges did not judge right, according to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law; and indeed if this Rule of yours was true, that becauſe the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in one Age did take the Common-Law to be otherways, than it was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in former Ages, that therefore the Common-Law was changed: The Judges then could never do contrary to the Common-Law, For, when they had declared (though erroneouſly) that the Common-Law ought to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therways taken, than it was formerly, the Common-Law by your Rule, would be thereupon changed, and what they did, would ever be legal, The abſurdity whereof every one may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily diſcern.</p>
            <p>What you ſay page 27, 28, 29, 30, and 31. to all thoſe Reaſons which I did give, to ſhew that whenſoever the word <hi>Mulier</hi> is uſed in the caſe of Frankmarriage, it ſhall by common-intendment be underſtood of a Woman that is of the <hi>Kindred,</hi> will, (I believe)
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97674:20"/>give no knowing perſon any ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at all; for though you pretend your ſelf to be very pleaſant, when you ſay <hi>you have ſeldom known (nor you believe any other) any ſuch queſtion as this, Whether</hi> Hugh Cyveliok <hi>had a former Wife, to be proved by argument of Scripture, or nicety of Law, which is meerly a queſtion of Hiſtory,</hi> yet certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the underſtanding Reader, will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily perceive that this is but a ſhift, and will alſo diſcern, that I did not bring that place of Scripture to prove that <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> had a former wife, but that I made uſe of it by way of <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,</hi> to take off what you had alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and I do not at all doubt, but that Text will fully ſatisfy, that all expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which ſeem Univerſal, are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to be expounded without any limitation at all; but as you would extend that expreſſion of <hi>Glanvill</hi> too far, ſo you run to the other extream concerning this of <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> 14.26. and would reſtrain theſe words, <hi>or for whatſoever thy ſoul deſireth,</hi> only to thoſe things there mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> Oxen, Sheep, Wine, and ſtrong Drink, which would be a <hi>Tautologie,</hi> and ſeveral times
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97674:20"/>in the ſame verſe give them liberty to make uſe of Oxen, Sheep, Wine, or ſtrong Drink, whereas undoubtedly the Jews at their ſaid Feaſts had alſo liberty to eat the Goat the Hart, Roe-Buck, Fallow Deer, Wild Goat, Pigarg, Wild Ox, the Chamois, as alſo all clean Fowls, Fiſhes, and other <hi>clean</hi> meats whatſoever, allowed them by their Law; and therefore this expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion being as univerſal as that of <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi> and yet being to be expounded, ſo as to agree with the Laws of that Kingdom, why ſhould not this ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing univerſal expreſſion of <hi>Glanvill</hi> be ſo expounded, as to agree with the Laws of our Kingdom? And if ſo, ſure what I ſay is to the point in hand.</p>
            <p>Alſo, If this Text of Scripture ſhould be reſtrained as you would have it, it would not contradict, but confirm what I ſaid; For, what expreſſion can ſeem more univerſal than this, <hi>viz. whatſoever thy ſoul deſireth,</hi> and yet you confeſs it ought not to be underſtood without ſome limitation, and indeed, you reſtrain it <hi>more</hi> than I do.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:97674:21"/>
            <p>And though it be true, that Baſtards both were and yet are capable of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Lands after they have gained a name by <hi>reputation,</hi> yet they are not capable of having Lands paſſed with them <hi>in libero maritogio,</hi> though it be paſſed with them by the name of Daughter, without the addition of Baſtard; and though you pretend that <hi>Amicia</hi> had gained a name by reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet you do not, nor cannot tell what it is, for certainly <hi>Amicia</hi> and <hi>Daughter</hi> are not any reputed names.</p>
            <p>Neither do I put my argument about <hi>Glanvil</hi>'s contradicting himſelf, as you put it, as will appear, pa. 34, and 35. of my former Book, ſo that you leave what I there ſay, wholly unanſwered. Neither do I ſay, that the Lawyers of latter ages do expound the Law, that Lands cannot paſs in Free-marriage with Baſtards now, <hi>ergo,</hi> it was ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in <hi>Glanvil</hi>'s time; but I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you many reaſons, why the Law was taken in the time of <hi>Glanvill,</hi> in the point of <hi>Free-Marriage,</hi> as it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken now; to which you give no other anſwer, but that you will leave it to wiſe Men to judge, who will take the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97674:21"/>paines to ſcan them, whether they be pertinent; And I do willingly appeal to all wiſe men, whether that be an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to thoſe Eight Reaſons, for if it be I am much miſtaken therein.</p>
            <p>But what will you ſay, (though I did admit it to be ſo, becauſe I would put the Caſe as hard as I could upon my ſelf) if <hi>Glanvil</hi> by thoſe words of his, <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Quilibet liber homo quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam partem terrae ſuae cum filia ſua, vel cum aliqua alia qualibet muliere dare po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt in Maritagium, ſive habuerit haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, ſive non, velit haeres vel non, imo &amp; eo contradicente</hi> did not ſay or mean that a man might give lands in <hi>Free-marriage</hi> with any woman whatſoever, but only that he might give lands with any wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in that kind of Marriage, which was not free; For, if you obſerve him well, he doth not there ſay, that any man what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever can give Lands <hi>in liberum mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagium</hi> with any woman whatſoever, but only that it may be ſo given with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny woman <hi>in Maritagium;</hi> Now that <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagium</hi> is two-fold, <hi>Glanvil</hi> himſelf tells you, <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. where he ſayes, <hi>Maritagium autem, aliud nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97674:22"/>liberum, aliud ſervitio obnoxiums liberum dicitur Maritagium quando ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis liber homo aliquam partem terrae ſuae dat cum aliqua muliere alicui in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagium ita quod ab omni ſervitio terra illa ſit quieta, &amp; a ſe &amp; haeredibus ſuis, verſus capitalem dominum acquietanda, &amp; in hac quidem libertate, ita ſtabit terra illa uſque ad tertium haeredem nec interim tenebuntur haeredes inde facere aliquod homagium, poſt tertium vero hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redem, ad debitum ſervitium terra ipſa revertetur, &amp; homagium inde capietur.</hi> Many of which words of <hi>Glanvil</hi> you may alſo find cited by my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> on <hi>Littleton, fol.</hi> 21. <hi>b.</hi> Now if you well obſerve it, <hi>Glanvil</hi> doth not there ſay that a man may give Lands <hi>in libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Maritagium cum qualibet muliere,</hi> but only <hi>in Maritagium;</hi> But when he ſpeaks of <hi>Free-marriage</hi> he uſeth the expreſſion <hi>cum aliqua muliere,</hi> with <hi>ſome woman,</hi> viz. one of the <hi>Kindred</hi> ſo that without doubt he uſing the ſame expreſſion with Mr. <hi>Bracton</hi> who was the next VVriter after him, he alſo underſtands it in the like manner, as the other did; But if Mr. <hi>Glanvill</hi>'s ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions (<hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.) had concerned
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97674:22"/>
               <hi>Free-marriage,</hi> yet I have formerly ſhewed, that the word <hi>Mulier</hi> in that caſe, could only have been underſtood of a woman of the <hi>Kindred:</hi> Alſo my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Littleton, fol.</hi> 21. <hi>b.</hi> when he hath told you that one of the four things incident to a Frank-marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age is, that the VVoman or Man that is the cauſe of the Gift, be <hi>of the blood</hi> of the <hi>Donour,</hi> not long after on the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of the ſame Page quotes <hi>Glanvil, lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. (the place on which you build) which he would never have done, if that place had been contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory to his opinion, and certainly, if <hi>Glanvills</hi> words in that place are to be underſtood as you would have them, they do contradict what my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> there ſayes, unleſs the Law in that point was taken after one manner in <hi>Glanvil</hi>'s time, and after another manner in my Lord <hi>Coke</hi>'s time, which if it had been ſo, my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> had been concerned to have taken notice thereof, having no otherway to reconcile it with what he had ſaid.</p>
            <p>What you ſay, <hi>pag.</hi> 32 <hi>&amp;</hi> 33. is not at all to the purpoſe; For, you there tell us, that <hi>Baſtard Sons, baſtard
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97674:23"/>Daughters, baſtard Brothers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in all Settlements and Conveyances of theſe laſt antient Ages, are termed Baſtards, but</hi> you ſay <hi>that was never uſed in the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Ages;</hi> But, this is only your bare ſaying, without any proof at all, ſo that your word herein will not paſs, unleſs you had ſhewed us ſeveral antient Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlements and Conveyances, in which, baſtard Sons, baſtard Daughters, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard Brothers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are named with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the word <hi>Baſtard</hi> joyned to them, which I am confident you cannot do, unleſs when very great perſons are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, who by reaſon of their greatneſs, are uſually excepted in ſuch caſes as thoſe; And indeed you do not only want proof to make good what you here ſay, but I have formerly brought proof of the contrary, from Sir <hi>Henry Spelman,</hi> who in his <hi>Gloſſary</hi> on the word <hi>Baſtardus,</hi> ſayes, <hi>Quoties enim agitur de honore vel commodo filiorum, appellatione ſiliorum non comprehendun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur baſtardi.</hi> And as to what you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that <hi>Baſtards be of the blood both now and in former ages, though the Law will not allow them ſo, becauſe they now are eſteemed in the eye of the Law quaſi
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97674:23"/>nullius filius; For if</hi> A. <hi>have a Baſtard Son or Daughter, which is really his, they muſt needs be of his blood: for no Law can extinguiſh Nature; though by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law they are not now eſteemed ſo;</hi> There is no force in what you ſo ſay, Becauſe, in this caſe Children are look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at, as they are in Law, and not as they are really, becauſe, it cannot be known what they are really; And therefore if <hi>A.</hi> have a baſtard child which is really his, yet it ſhall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit, becauſe it is in Law <hi>nullius fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us;</hi> and on the other ſide, If <hi>A.</hi> have a Wife who doth play falſe with him, and hath a Child begotten of her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by another man, yet this Child ſhall inherit, becauſe it is in Law the Child of <hi>A.</hi> And whereas you alſo ask the Queſtion, What if you ſay that <hi>the reaſon why in the Deeds of thoſe elder Ages, they were called Daughters, without any addition of Baſtard, whereby the party owned them to be of their blood, was, that the Lands paſſed</hi> in libero ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagio <hi>with ſuch might deſcend to their heires? For our Lawyers now tell us, that Baſtards are capable of receiving Lands, after they have gained a Name by reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97674:24"/>Why may not then Baſtards, having gained the names of Daughters, receive a grant from their owned Fathers, either in Frank-marriage or otherwayes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your Queſtion will be eaſily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, becauſe the conſideration of the Gift in <hi>Free-marriage</hi> is the blood that is betwixt the <hi>Donour,</hi> and that <hi>Donee</hi> with whom the Land is given; But a Baſtard is not <hi>de ſanguine patris</hi> (<hi>Dyer, Fol.</hi> 374. <hi>b.</hi>) and the calling of any perſon <hi>Daughter,</hi> who is not ſo in Law, will not make her of the blood, for if that would ſerve, a Man might call any other Woman his Daughter, that is not ſo, and then give Lands with her in <hi>Frank-marriage:</hi> Beſides, to what purpoſe ſhould ſuch tricks as theſe be uſed, which will not hold, when though a Man cannot give Lands in <hi>Free-marriage</hi> with his Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard Daughter, yet there are other wayes, whereby any Man that pleaſes and hath a diſpoſing power, may ſettle Lands on a Baſtard Daughter and her heires: Alſo, if <hi>Glanvills</hi> words did prove, as you would pretend they do, To what purpoſe ſhould men in thoſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97674:24"/>ages, leave the word <hi>Bastard</hi> out of their Deeds of <hi>Free-marriage</hi> to their baſtard Daughters, with deſign there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to cauſe ſuch lands to continue to them and their heirs, if ſuch gifts might be made with any woman what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; ſo that you never obſerve how finely you have argued here, againſt your ſelf.</p>
            <p>VVhere you ſay, in the 34, 35, 36 and 37 <hi>Pages</hi> of your <hi>Book,</hi> that <hi>though you do not find</hi> Geva <hi>called a Baſtard in expreſs terms, yet you find it implyed in an Author contemporary</hi> (meaning <hi>Orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus) by certain and ſure conſequence, which you believe can never be fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered;</hi> and for the fortifying of which, you pretend to give ſome reaſons; Give me leave (ſince you give the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion) again to ſay, what I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſaid, <hi>viz.</hi> that though <hi>Orderi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Hugh Lupus</hi> his death, doth add theſe words, <hi>Richardus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem pulcherrimus puer quem ſolum ex</hi> Ermentrude <hi>filia</hi> Hugonis <hi>de</hi> Clara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monte <hi>genuit.</hi> I am not yet ſatisfied, but that he might as well mean, that he was the only Son which Earl <hi>Hugh</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:97674:25"/>had by <hi>Ermentrude,</hi> as that he was the only child that he had by her; For there is no neceſſity to take the word <hi>ſolum</hi> adverbially, neither is it marked as an Adverb in <hi>Ordericus</hi> his Book, though it be ſo in yours, and yet in his Book, Adverbs are uſually mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; And though you alleadg that <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericus</hi> doth not ſay <hi>quem ſolum filium, as I interpret him, but indefinitly, quent ſolum ex</hi> Ermentrude <hi>genuit, and ſo, whether ſolum be underſtood adverbially, or whether it be taken for a Noun, no more can be made of it in Engliſh than thus,</hi> Richard <hi>a beautiful youth whom only Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>begot on</hi> Ermentrude, <hi>&amp;c. and ſo, whether we Engliſh it, whom only he begot, or whom he only begot, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the ſame ſenſe, and ſhews that no other perſon, either Son or Daughter, was begotten on</hi> Ermentrude <hi>by Earl</hi> Hugh. You muſt give me leave to diſſent from you herein; For, I conceive this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of <hi>quem ſolum genuit,</hi> doth amount to as much as if he had ſaid <hi>quem ſolum filium genuit,</hi> which if it do, then (notwithſtanding the ſaid expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> might poſſibly have a Daughter or Daughters by the ſaid
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97674:25"/>
               <hi>Ermentrude;</hi> For, to what Antecedent can the word <hi>quem</hi> ſo properly relate, as to the word <hi>puer?</hi> and if ſo, then <hi>quem ſolum puerum</hi> is as much as <hi>quem ſolum filium,</hi> and ſo doth not exclude him from having a Daughter or Daughters by the ſaid <hi>Ermentrude;</hi> For, though the word <hi>puer</hi> be by ſome underſtood to ſignifie a Child of either Sex, as you alſo ſeem to take it in your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities, p.</hi> 113 &amp; 114. (But miſprinted 121 <hi>&amp;</hi> 122.) Yet Mr. <hi>Gouldman</hi> in his Dictionary will tell you that it is a miſtake, where on the word <hi>puer</hi> he thus writes, <hi>Nonnullis habetur communis generis, ſed male, ex Ovidiano illo Carmine, de Iphide puella in puerum mutata;</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Dona puer ſolvit quae faeminavoverat Iphis.</q>
            <p>And though you ſay, that <hi>Geva could not be by any former Wife, becauſe Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>had never any other Wife;</hi> Yet that is more than either you or I know, for, there were many things done in thoſe Ages which never came to our knowledges. And therefore I do not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97674:26"/>take upon me to tell, whether <hi>Geva</hi> was by a former Wife than <hi>Ermentrude,</hi> or whether ſhe was by <hi>Ermentrude,</hi> or whether ſhe was a Baſtard, But I ſay, ſhe might be any of the three, for any thing that you have yet proved, and ſo long as it is uncertain what ſhe was, you can bring no conſiderable Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from her againſt <hi>Amicia;</hi> And if you could prove her a Baſtard, it would ſignifie nothing, becauſe the Deed made to her, is not a gift in <hi>Frank-marriage</hi> (as hath formerly and will hereafter appear.)</p>
            <p>And whereas you ask, <hi>p.</hi> 36. <hi>Being I expound the words of</hi> Ordericus <hi>to be, that Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>had no other Son, What advantage it is to my purpoſe, unleſs</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va <hi>was that Daughter, and was legitimate?</hi> I anſwer, That poſſibly <hi>Geva</hi> might be that Daughter, or poſſibly <hi>Geva</hi> might be by a former Wife, and that Daughter which Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had by <hi>Ermentrude,</hi> might die before Earl <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard,</hi> ſo that nothing of certainty can be gathered from ſuch Arguments as theſe.</p>
            <p>As to what you ſay, <hi>p.</hi> 38, 39, 40 <hi>&amp;</hi> 41. that <hi>I am not to argue upon poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97674:26"/>and becauſe it might poſſibly be ſo, to ſay, that the Earldome of</hi> Cheſter <hi>was antiently entayled on the heires Males;</hi> I Anſwer, That I do not poſitively aver any ſuch thing, But let the caſe be how it will, and whetherſoever <hi>Geva</hi> or <hi>Randle de Meſchines</hi> was the heir ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral to <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> it ſeems to me that the ſaid Earldome, did not come by deſcent, to the heir general, whoever that was; For, it clearly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that <hi>Geva</hi> had it not, and <hi>Randle de Meſchines</hi> had it not by deſcent; For, if what <hi>James York</hi> in his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Honour, p.</hi> 105. ſayes, be true, <hi>Randle de Meſchines</hi> was made Earl by Grant of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt; and <hi>Ordericus p.</hi> 876. tells us, that he reſtored to the ſaid King <hi>Henry,</hi> all the Land which he had by his Wife the Widow of <hi>Roger</hi> de <hi>Romara,</hi> for the Earldom of <hi>Cheſter;</hi> which was more than was needful for him to do, if he had a good title there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by deſcent.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ask me, <hi>Why may I think that the King (though he gave it to</hi> Randle) <hi>did not give the honour and lands unto him, as in whom was the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97674:27"/>right to have it?</hi> and do ſay, that <hi>to this I give no anſwer at all.</hi> I may well tell you, that I could not give an Anſwer, until you did ask the Queſtion, and you never asked the Queſtion in your former Book; But the Anſwer which I ſhall now give to this Queſtion, is, That I ſuppoſe, Kings in ſuch caſes do that, which to them ſeems moſt juſt, but yet Kings in theſe caſes, as well as in others, are of different Judgments from one another very many times, and indeed the very ſame Princes will be ſometimes of one mind, and ſometimes of another mind, concerning the ſame thing; And thus we ſee, when <hi>Randle Blundevile</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> dyed, which was in the year 1232. King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third did ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the four Siſters of the ſaid Earl <hi>Randle,</hi> who were of the whole blood, to inherit that eſtate, and the ſaid Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome went to <hi>John Scot</hi> ſon of <hi>David</hi> Earl of <hi>Huntingdon</hi> in right of <hi>Maud</hi> his Mother, the eldeſt of the ſaid four Siſters; But when the ſaid <hi>John Scot</hi> dyed, which was in the year 1237, the ſaid King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third would not ſuffer the ſaid Earldome of <hi>Cheſter</hi> to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97674:27"/>come to any of the Sons of any of the Siſters of the ſaid <hi>John Scot,</hi> though he had before permitted it to come to the Son of the eldeſt Siſter of the ſaid <hi>Randle Blundevile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, that <hi>if</hi> Geva <hi>had been but of the half-blood, ſhe woul'd by all probability have buſled hard for ſo great an Eſtate in thoſe Ages, before ſhe had loſt it.</hi> I do wonder very much at what you ſay, Becauſe, any Coſen that is of the whole blood (how many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees ſoever the diſtance is) will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit at Law, before a Brother or Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that is but of the half-blood; And whereas you ſay, <hi>I am come to an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent way of arguing, by ifs, and ands, and poſſibilities, by which means Anſwers may be made to any thing even to eternity.</hi> I do not offer from thoſe kinds of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or Anſwers, to determine any thing certainly, but only make uſe of them to ſhew the uncertainty of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things which you urge; But, you pretend certainties from ſuch kind of Arguments, and particularly in this caſe of <hi>Amicia:</hi> For, all the reaſons which you alleadg againſt her would not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97674:28"/>prove her to be a Baſtard, if thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments that are brought on her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half were all laid aſide.</p>
            <p>In your Anſwer to my <hi>Defence</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micia, p.</hi> 42 &amp; 43. you again cavil with me, without any juſt cauſe, and ſay, <hi>that the caſe that I did there put, comes as near to the caſe of</hi> Geva, <hi>as an Apple to an Oyſter,</hi> But whether it be ſo as you ſay, let the Reader judge. In your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities, p.</hi> 136. (which words of yours are alſo in the 10 <hi>&amp;</hi> 11 <hi>pages</hi> of my <hi>Defence</hi> of <hi>Amicia</hi>) you have theſe words, viz. <hi>And howbeit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Earldomes have deſcended to the heires Males, and not to the heires general, yet in this caſe were no heires Male, but two Females, an Aunt legitimate, who had it, and a Siſter not legitimate, and ſhew me a precedent whereever the heires of an Aunt inherited before the heires of a Siſter, both legally born and no heires-male left, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in caſe of forfeiture by Treaſon, or ſome other great cauſe to hinder the ſame.</hi> From theſe words of yours, I did not offer to raiſe any cavil, by telling you, that though honours or lands may be given to any perſons whatſoever, by
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97674:28"/>thoſe who have power to diſpoſe of the ſame, that yet they cannot properly be ſaid to deſcend to any but to the next heires, and therefore in point of <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent,</hi> it is impoſſible that any one that is further off, ſhould be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another that is nearer; Neither did I tell you, how you did name an <hi>Aunt</hi> legitimate, in ſtead of the <hi>Son</hi> of an Aunt legitimate that had it; But I ſuppoſing (as I think any other would have done from theſe words of yours) that your meaning was, that <hi>Randle de Meſchines</hi> muſt needs have more right to ſucceed in that Earldom of <hi>Cheſter</hi> than <hi>Geva</hi> had, becauſe, the ſaid <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle</hi> did enjoy the ſame, and that you thought it to be very clear, that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever there were no heirs-Male left, if the honour went to any of the Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, the <hi>King</hi> did alwayes prefer that perſon who was next of blood to it, except in caſe of Treaſon, or the like, and did thereupon deſire me to ſhew you a precedent to the contrary, if I ſo could, and you inſtancing in the <hi>Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and not in the Lands, I did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhew you where one that was a <hi>Baron</hi> by Writ, dyed without heir Male,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97674:29"/>leaving two Siſters only, and the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronry</hi> came to the Husband of the younger Siſter, and not to the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of the elder Siſter, it being the pleaſure of the King to call Sir <hi>Hunt Bourcher,</hi> who had Marryed the younger Siſter, to the Parliament, and not to call Sir <hi>Thomas Nevil,</hi> who had Marryed the elder Siſter; And if this be not a like caſe to that of <hi>Geva</hi> and Earl <hi>Randle</hi> (if <hi>Geva</hi> was legitimate) I am ſtill very much miſtaken; And whereas you now demand of me, If <hi>Geva</hi> was legitimate, Why the <hi>Lands</hi> of <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> did not come to her, whatever the Earldom did: Though I cannot give you the certain reaſon, becauſe the thing was done ſo long ſince, yet I can ſhew you ſeveral poſſibilities why they might not; For, either it might be the will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the then King, that <hi>Randle de Meſchines</hi> ſhould have the Eſtate as well as Earldome, and that <hi>Geva</hi> ſhould have recompence made her ſome other way, (as the Siſters of <hi>John Scot</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> in the like caſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards had) or perhaps ſhe might be of the half-blood to Earl <hi>Richard,</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:97674:29"/>and <hi>Randle de Meſchines</hi> be heir at Law before her, or perhaps the ſaid Ear I <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> having a greater kindneſs for the ſaid Earl <hi>Randle</hi> than he had for <hi>Geva,</hi> (there being ſometimes great unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes betwixt Brothers and Siſters) might give his Eſtate to the ſaid <hi>Randle de Meſchines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe Arguments of mine which you mention <hi>p.</hi> 44. and are pretended to be Anſwered by you, <hi>pag.</hi> 45, 46 <hi>&amp;</hi> 47. remain yet in their greateſt ſtrength, and are not at all anſwered by you, nay, the one of them is ſo farr from being anſwered, that it is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by you, unleſs you only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to underſtand it, becauſe, you perceive you cannot give an anſwer to it, and I rather think that to be the truth of the caſe, Becauſe you have not recited my Argument as I did expreſs it; For you recite it thus; Becauſe <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Littleton, fo.</hi> 21. <hi>b.</hi> tells us that theſe words <hi>in liberum Maritaginm are words of Art, and ſo are neceſſarily required:</hi> and there you break off ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly; Whereas I told you that the Deed which you alleadged to be made
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97674:30"/>to <hi>Geva</hi> would not at all concern <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> if <hi>Geva</hi> was a baſtard, becauſe it was no gift in Frank-marriage, as that gift to <hi>Amicia</hi> was; And for a proof thereof I told you, that my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Littleton</hi> in the place aboveſaid did tell you, that <hi>theſe words</hi> in libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum maritagium <hi>are ſuch words of Art, and ſo neceſſarily required</hi> (in theſe kind of gifts) <hi>as they cannot be expreſſed by words equipollent, or amounting to as much;</hi> And he alſo there gave you the reaſon, which was, that theſe words <hi>in liberum Maritagium</hi> did create an Eſtate of Inheritance, againſt the general Rule of the Law, and therefore the Law required, that it ſhould be legally purſued; And to explain this, he alſo ſaid, that <hi>if a man give Lands to another with his Daughter,</hi> in connubio ſoluto ab omni ſervitio, <hi>&amp;c. yet there paſseth in this caſe but an Eſtate for life;</hi> For although thoſe words be the ſame in ſenſe, as the words <hi>in libero maritagio</hi> be, yet being not the very ſame words, they do not create an Eſtate of Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; But you contrary to all this, would not believe my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> if he ſhould have ſaid that the words <hi>in libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97674:30"/>conjugio</hi> did make but an Eſtate for life, (which he hath indeed by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence ſaid) But you will have the words <hi>liberum conjugium</hi> to create an Eſtate of Inheritance, as well as the words <hi>liberum maritagium</hi> (which no man before you ever ſaid) Whereas no words that are equipollent, or amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to as much can do it, it being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to make an Eſtate in <hi>Free-mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi> if there be wanting either the word <hi>liberum,</hi> or the word <hi>Maritagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo, as the words <hi>in libero conjugio</hi> can make but an Eſtate for life, ſo it is alſo clear, that in your Deed of Earl <hi>Randle</hi> to <hi>Ceva,</hi> there was no more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended than an Eſtate for life, it run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all along in the ſingular number <hi>Et teneat bene &amp; in pace.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ut melius &amp; liberius tenuit,</hi> And it is likely the Deed of Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> did run after the ſame manner, by that expreſſion <hi>ſicuti Comes</hi> Hughes <hi>ei in libero conjugio dedit,</hi> But I believe the <hi>Baſſets</hi> did afterwards enjoy the ſaid lands, though how, or by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of what Deed, I am not able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare; For, in <hi>Monaſticon Anglica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97674:31"/>Part</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 439, and in your <hi>Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Antiquities, p.</hi> 113. (but miſprinted 121.) I find <hi>Geffrey Ridell</hi> and <hi>Ralph Baſſet</hi> called the heires of the ſaid <hi>Geva;</hi> Now if thoſe perſons were the heires of her body, and the aforeſaid Deed a Gift in <hi>Frank-marriage,</hi> Why did not Earl <hi>Randle</hi> confirm or grant thoſe lands to her heires, as well as to her, And if they were not the heirs of her body, ſhe could not be a <hi>baſtard,</hi> For, as my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> on <hi>Littleton, fol.</hi> 3. <hi>b.</hi> tells you, <hi>A Baſtard can have no heir but of his own body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas I brought another Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to prove that this Gift of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va</hi> could not be a Gift in <hi>Frank-marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,</hi> Becauſe my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſays, that one of the things incident to a Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marriage is, that the <hi>Donees</hi> ſhall hold freely of the <hi>Donour</hi> till the fourth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree be paſt, which cannot be in <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va</hi>'s caſe, Becauſe there was no <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nees,</hi> but one <hi>Donee</hi> only, and the Eſtate could not continue until the Fourth degree was paſt, becauſe it was onely for <hi>Geva</hi>'s life; You tell me that my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Littleton, fol.</hi> 21. <hi>b. ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:97674:31"/>Peter Saltmarch's <hi>Caſe, and</hi> Fitz-Herbert <hi>de natura brevium, fol.</hi> 172. <hi>that lands may be given by a Man to his Son in Free-marriage, and why not to his Daughter alone in Free-marriage?</hi> But I pray you, How can there be a Gift in <hi>Free-marriage,</hi> if there be no <hi>Marriage</hi> at all? and, How can there be a <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi> if the Man or Woman be <hi>alone?</hi> But you miſunderſtand this place (as you do many others) For, my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> if you obſerve him well, doth not there ſay, that ſuch a Gift can be made with a Man <hi>alone,</hi> or with a Woman <hi>alone,</hi> But there tells you, <hi>that a gift in free-marriage may be either to a Man with a woman, or as ſome have held, to a Woman with a Man,</hi> and for proof there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, cites <hi>Peter Saltmarſh</hi> his caſe, and <hi>Fitz-Herbert;</hi> And this is no more than what I ſaid in the 49 <hi>Page</hi> of my former <hi>Book,</hi> where I alſo ſhewed you how <hi>Bracton</hi> did therewith accord; But there is none of them that ſaith as you do, That land may be given in <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marriage</hi> to a Man without a Woman, or to a VVoman without a Man.</p>
            <p>In your 48 <hi>&amp;</hi> 49 <hi>Pages,</hi> you would willingly perſwade the Reader that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97674:32"/>
               <hi>Earl</hi> Randle <hi>de</hi> Gernoniis <hi>Father to Earl</hi> Hugh Cyveliok <hi>was Marryed by</hi> Robert <hi>Earl of</hi> Glouceſter <hi>unto</hi> Maude <hi>his Daughter, thereby to draw him to the part of Queen</hi> Maude <hi>his Siſter, about the very year</hi> 1139. <hi>before which time we find no mention in our antient Hiſtorians of</hi> Randle's <hi>acting againſt King</hi> Stephen, <hi>but in that very year we do, and then by ſome of them ſtiled Son-in-law to the Earl of</hi> Glouceſter. But I pray you, VVhy is it not full as likely, that <hi>before</hi> that time, <hi>Randle de Gernoniis</hi> was Marryed to the Daughter of the ſaid Earl of <hi>Gloucester,</hi> and thereby was the more eaſily drawn to that party, to which he ſtood ſo near related, as that, that match ſhould be made <hi>purpoſely</hi> to draw him to that party? And how could you hear much of that Earl <hi>Randle</hi>'s actings againſt King <hi>Stephen,</hi> before the year 1139? ſeeing <hi>Gervaſius</hi> a <hi>Benedictine Monke of</hi> Canterbury (who lived in the Reign of King <hi>John</hi>) tells us, in his <hi>Chronicles</hi> or <hi>Annalls, col.</hi> 1345. <hi>l.</hi> 60. that it was in the year 1138, when <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Glouceſter did begin to quarrel with the ſaid King</hi> Stephen.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:97674:32"/>
            <p>And whereas you yet ſeem unſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> was of ſuch an age as probably to have had another Wife before <hi>Bertred,</hi> and do now ſay, <hi>p.</hi> 49. <hi>if we reckon by</hi> utmoſt poſſibilities, <hi>that Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>could not poſſibly be above ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen or ſeventeen years older than</hi> Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred; I do very much wonder thereat, ſeeing I have formerly from the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which you uſed to prove it to be otherwayes, made it manifeſt, that he might poſſibly be ſeveral years above double her age, and that ſo clearly, that I am confident, no man beſides your ſelf, will offer to deny the ſame; For I then told you that whether the Marriage of <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> with <hi>Mabill</hi> Daughter and heir of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Fitz-Hamon</hi> was according to <hi>Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> in the year 1109. or according to <hi>Stow</hi> in the year 1110. the ſaid <hi>Mabill</hi> might have <hi>Maude</hi> her ſecond Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the year 1112, which <hi>Maude</hi> if ſhe was Marryed to Earl <hi>Randle de Gernoniis</hi> in the year 1128, when ſhe was ſixteen years of age, might have her Son <hi>Hugh Cyvelick</hi> in the year 1129. which if true, the ſaid Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> was
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97674:33"/>fifty two years old at his death, For he died in the year 1181, and if ſo, then he was four years above twice the age of <hi>Bertred,</hi> For ſhe was but Twenty four years old when the ſaid Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> died, as appears, <hi>Rot. de Dominabus pue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in Scacc. penes Remem. R. ſub Tit. Linc. Rot.</hi> 1. And it is certain, that the ſaid Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> was Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> about four years before his VVife <hi>Bertred</hi> was born, beſides what age he was of, when his Father died, and his Daughter <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micia</hi> was Married in his life time, and none knows how many years before his death. And if the Marriage of the ſaid <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> with the ſaid <hi>Mabill</hi> was in the year 1109. then he might poſſibly be Five years above double the age of his VVife <hi>Bertred;</hi> And this is the more likely to be true, Becauſe, though Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> be a later VVriter, than Mr. <hi>Stow</hi> is, yet Mr. <hi>Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> cites one that lived long before Mr. <hi>Stow,</hi> as will appear by the old Engliſh Rithmical Story, attributed to one <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> and recited in the 647. <hi>Page</hi> of Mr. <hi>Seldens</hi> Titles of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:97674:33"/>
            <p>In your <hi>Anſwer, pag.</hi> 50, 51, 52 <hi>&amp;</hi> 53. you endeavor to weaken the Third and Fourth reaſons which were brought as concurrent proof on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of <hi>Amicia,</hi> by ſaying, <hi>that</hi> Hugh Cyveliok<hi>'s Wife was a witneſs to her Husbands Deed, which a Wife cannot now be, ſhe being not capable to be a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, either for or againſt her Husband,</hi> whereby you would inſinuate a change of the Law in that particular from what it was formerly, and you alſo ſay, <hi>that if</hi> Hugh Cyveliok <hi>had had a former Wife, ſure</hi> Raph Mainwaring <hi>would have called his Daughter after her, and not after the then Counteſs;</hi> And you there make nothing of <hi>Roger Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring</hi>'s calling <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> and <hi>Lincoln</hi> his Uncle in a Deed, nor of <hi>Henry de Audley</hi>'s being a Witneſs to the Deeds of <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> and <hi>Lincoln,</hi> and of <hi>Robert de Ferrars,</hi> (which later you ſay is far fetcht) nor of <hi>Raph Mainwarings</hi> and <hi>Roger Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warings</hi> being Witneſſes to ſo many Deeds of thoſe that were Earles of <hi>Cheſter</hi> in their times.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:97674:34"/>
            <p>But to theſe things, I ſay, that the Law is ſtill the ſame as it was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the particular by you here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; For, both antiently and at this day alſo, I know nothing that hinders, but that the Wife may ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe as a Witneſs to a Deed which her Husband doth make, and though ſhe neither antiently could, nor yet can be a witneſs for or againſt her Husband, yet there is this uſe of it, that if the Wife ſurvive her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and it come to be controverted amongſt other parties, whether ſuch a Deed was Sealed by him, or not, ſhe in the time of her VVidowhood, may be a good VVitneſs for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And as to the calling of Sir <hi>Raph Mainwarings</hi> Daughter by the name of <hi>Bertred</hi> after the preſent Counteſs, and not after the name of <hi>Hugh Cyvelioks</hi> firſt VVife; That is no wonder at all, it being more ordinary to call Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters after their Godmothers Names, than after the names of their own Grandmothers, and eſpecially when the Godmothers are of great quality; Now the ſaid <hi>Amicia</hi>'s Daughter being
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97674:34"/>called <hi>Bertred</hi> (which is a very unuſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al name) it is more than probable, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what you expreſſed to me under your hand in <hi>April</hi> 1664.) that <hi>Bertred</hi> the Counteſs was Godmother to the ſaid <hi>Bertred Mainwaring,</hi> And if ſo, it is very unlikely that <hi>Amicia</hi> was illegitimate; For VVives are ſeldome Godmothers to their Husbands Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards, or to the Children of ſuch Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards.</p>
            <p>Alſo, Sir <hi>Raph Mainwaring</hi> and Sir <hi>Roger Mainwaring</hi> and <hi>Henry de Aud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> the Sou-in-law of the ſaid Sir <hi>Raph Mainwaring</hi> being ſo often VVitneſſes to the Deeds of the Earls of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and to the Deeds of their very near Relations, doth certainly ſhew there was then a very great and conſtant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timacy betwixt the ſaid Families.</p>
            <p>And though you pretend that Sir <hi>Raph Mainwaring</hi> was very converſant with the Earle, becauſe he was Judge, and therefore came ſo often to be a VVitneſs, and ſay, that <hi>we may find the like number of Charters or more, to which</hi> Philip Orreby <hi>Judge of</hi> Cheſter <hi>was witneſs in like nature;</hi> I conceive that you are deceived therein, although
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:97674:35"/>
               <hi>Philip Orreby</hi> was Judge of <hi>Cheſter</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps longer than Sir <hi>Raph Mainwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> was; For I do believe that I can make it to appear by what Deeds I have, and what Deeds I have ſeen of others, that Sir <hi>Raph Maeinwaring</hi> and his Son Sir <hi>Roger Mainwaring</hi> were wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to more Deeds of <hi>Hugh Cyvelioks</hi> and <hi>Randle Blundevil</hi> than any other perſons of any one Family were; Add hereunto (which I have in my former Book mentioned) that Sir <hi>Roger Mainwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> in a Deed of his own calls <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> and <hi>Lincoln</hi> his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle,</hi> and how I did there obſerve, that though the VVriters of Hiſtories, did ſometimes give to Baſtards, the name of Coſen, Brother, Uncle, Son, and Daughter, I did believe you could hardly find any one that you could cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly prove to be a Baſtard, or the Son of a Baſtard, that did preſume in a Deed to call ſo great a perſon as the Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> was, his Brother or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, unleſs he came to be a very great Perſon himſelf; And this is ſo true, that in the 53 <hi>Page</hi> you are forced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that ſuch Precedents are ſcant, but yet you think you have found one,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97674:35"/>viz. <hi>Randle de Eſtbury,</hi> or <hi>Aſtbury,</hi> who in a Deed mentioned in the <hi>Addenda</hi> of your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities</hi> is called, <hi>the Earl of</hi> Cheſter<hi>'s Nephew, and is put the laſt of all the witneſſes, and was certainly but an ordinary Gentleman, nor Knight nor Lord.</hi> But this Precedent will fail you, for two Reaſons, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you do as good as confeſs that you cannot prove him to be a Baſtard, (and he might perhaps be a younger Brother, or Son of a younger Brother, and ſo not neceſſarily a Knight or a Lord) And <hi>Secondly.</hi> Becauſe he doth not call himſelf the Earles Nephew, but is called ſo by others, and that is ſo far from contradicting, that it doth confirm what I ſaid in my former <hi>Book;</hi> Alſo if you obſerve it, there were no VVitneſſes to the ſaid Deed, beſides the ſaid <hi>Randle de Aſtbury,</hi> except <hi>David de Malpas</hi> (whom I conceive was <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> of <hi>Malpas</hi>) and <hi>William</hi> his Son.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>you ſhould be glad to find out the Extraction of the ſaid</hi> Randle <hi>de</hi> Aſtbury, <hi>if he were not a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard.</hi> Though it be perhaps impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble now to tell you his Extraction cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, becauſe he lived ſo long ſince,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97674:36"/>and we only find him mentioned as a witneſs in one Ded, Yet I doubt not but to ſatisfie the Reader, that he and his Father and Mother might all be Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimate, For, (not to ſay, that he might be a Son of ſome other Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſaid <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> by his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer VVife) he might poſſibly be the Son of <hi>Roger,</hi> Son of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok;</hi> And I know no great reaſon why the ſaid <hi>Roger</hi> ſhould by you be ſuſpected to be a baſtard, For, you only find him (as appears by your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, p.</hi> 134. and in my Firſt <hi>Book, p.</hi> 1.) mentioned <hi>as a Witneſs to a Deed of his Brother</hi> Randle<hi>'s, to the Abbey of Saint</hi> VVerburge: So that you conceive him to be a baſtard, Becauſe neither he, nor any iſſue-Male of his, ſucceeded in the Earldome of <hi>Cheſter</hi> after the death of <hi>Randle Blundevil,</hi> VVhereas the ſaid <hi>Roger</hi> might be lawful, and be Father to this <hi>Randle de Aſtbury,</hi> and yet both he and the ſaid <hi>Randle de Aſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> might dye before the ſaid <hi>Randle de Blundevil,</hi> For he lived very long, and was Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> above Fifty years; Alſo it is very ſtrange, if <hi>Amicia</hi> was a Baſtard, and the Father or
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97674:36"/>Mother of the ſaid <hi>Randle de Aſtbury</hi> was alſo a Baſtard, that thoſe Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards could find none to call their Children after, but the then <hi>Counteſs,</hi> and the then <hi>Earl,</hi> For the Daughter of <hi>Amicia</hi> was called <hi>Bertred</hi> after <hi>Randle Blundevill</hi>'s Mother, and <hi>Randle de Astbury</hi> was of the ſame Name with the ſaid Earl; But admitting that the ſaid <hi>Roger</hi> was a Baſtard, Why might not <hi>Randle de Aſtbury</hi> however be his Son? and then, What neceſſity (of what you ſay in your <hi>Addenda</hi>) of either finding out another Baſe Son, or another Baſe Daughter of the ſaid <hi>Hugh Cyveliok;</hi> But you have been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry willing to charge him with many Baſtards both Sons and Daughters, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I find no great Reaſon to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that he had any at all unleſs <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganus de Milton,</hi> and it is poſſible in that caſe, you having neither the Deed, nor a Copy of the Deed by you, that you might take <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> for <hi>Hugh Lupus,</hi> as well as in another Deed (as will anon appear) you did take <hi>Randle Blundevil</hi> for <hi>Randle de Gernoniis.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:97674:37"/>
            <p>I am ſtill of the ſame opinion that I was formerly of, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Richard Bacuns</hi> Mother was not a Baſe Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Hugh Gyveliok,</hi> nor any Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his at all, but that ſhe was daughter to <hi>Randle Meſchines,</hi> and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to <hi>Randle de Gernoniis;</hi> And I think thoſe reaſons which I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in my former Book do fully prove the ſame. And albeit you tell me in the 54, 55, and 56 pages of your latter Book, that <hi>truly I am deceived in it,</hi> yet I do not doubt but to ſatisfy all the world, that it is you (and not I) that are deceived therein; And whereas you ſay, <hi>it is true (as I obſerve) that there was no ſuch Archbiſhop of</hi> York <hi>called</hi> Will. <hi>nor Biſhop of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>whoſe Chriſtian name began with</hi> R. <hi>both living at one time, either in the time of</hi> Randle de Blundevill <hi>or</hi> Randle de Gernoniis. I anſwer, I did make no ſuch obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all, but the contrary, For, I ſhewed you that in the time of <hi>Randle de Gernoniis; William,</hi> Siſters Son to King <hi>Stephen,</hi> was Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> for a time, <hi>viz.</hi> about 1142 or 1143. (though he was afterwards ouſted of it
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:97674:37"/>again till 1152. or 1153.) and <hi>Roger Clinton</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Coventry</hi> and <hi>Litchfield,</hi> (which then was the ſame with the Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi>) from the year 1128, until the year 1148 or 1149. And I then alſo told you, that there was no <hi>William,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>York</hi> at anytime during the life of <hi>Randle Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devill,</hi> nor any man Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> whoſe Chriſtian name began with <hi>R.</hi> except <hi>Richard Peche,</hi> who died about the time that <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> died, <hi>viz.</hi> in 1182 (though ſome ſay, in 1181. and ſome in 1183.) at which time <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Blundevill</hi> could not be of age to Seal any kind of Deed, becauſe <hi>Bertred</hi> the ſaid <hi>Randle</hi>'s Mother, was then but about Twenty five years old; and this Argument you perceive to be ſo ſtrong againſt you in this point, that you have no way to avoid it, but by giving a ſtrange anſwer to it, which is, that <hi>you do conceive the Roll from whence the Deed in</hi> Monaſticon (Par. 2. Pa. 267.) <hi>is written, is miſtaken in</hi> Will, and <hi>R. and miſwrit therein from the Original Chart it ſelf;</hi> Which liberty if a Man might take, he might anſwer any thing in the world; and your reaſon
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:97674:38"/>for ſo ſaying is, <hi>Becauſe</hi> Richard Bacun <hi>in his ſaid Deed doth ſay, that he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the warranty of</hi> Randle <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter <hi>his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle, for the ratifying of that Grant; and the very next Deed fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in the Roll, and tranſcribed in the</hi> Monaſticon, <hi>is the Deed of</hi> Randle <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>with Confirmation and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranty accordingly, whereunto</hi> Roger La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>Conſtable of</hi> Cheſhire <hi>is a witneſs, who only lived in the time of</hi> Randle Blundevill, <hi>and no other Earl of</hi> Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>as I may ſee cleerly proved among the Barons of</hi> Halton <hi>in your Book, nor is there any other Deed of Confirmation and Warranty to be found by any Earl, ſave this; wherefore</hi> (you ſay) <hi>certainly it muſt be</hi> Randle Blundevil <hi>whom</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Bacun <hi>calleth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle in his own Deed of the Foundation of the ſaid Prio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> And you alſo ſay, <hi>the Biſhop of</hi> Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter (<hi>being alſo Biſhop of</hi> Litchfield <hi>and</hi> Coventry <hi>at that time</hi>) <hi>he was not then ſubject to the juriſdiction of</hi> York <hi>but</hi> Canterbury; and you alſo ſay, <hi>That there was no Archbiſhop of</hi> York <hi>called</hi> Will. <hi>nor Biſhop of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>whoſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian name began with</hi> R. <hi>both living at one time, either in the time of</hi> Randle
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:97674:38"/>Blundevill <hi>or</hi> Randle de Gernoniis, <hi>that you can find.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That it is not to be doubted, but that <hi>Richard Bacun</hi> did obtain the Warranty and Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of that <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> who was his Uncle, and then living; neither is it to be doubted, but that the Deed, to which <hi>Roger</hi> Conſtable of <hi>Cheſhire</hi> was a witneſs, was the Deed of <hi>Randle Blundevil,</hi> I having proved it to be ſo, in the 56 page of my former Book, becauſe <hi>Roger</hi> Conſtable of <hi>Cheſhire</hi> was living in the time of no other <hi>Randle</hi> but <hi>Randle Blundevil,</hi> ſo that you did not need to ſend me to ſee that clearly proved among the Barons of <hi>Halton in your Book;</hi> but the Deed of Confirmation of that Earl who was Uncle of <hi>Richard Bacun,</hi> is not in the <hi>Monaſticon,</hi> but was proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly loſt, as many other antient Deeds were: and that Deed of <hi>Randle Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devill,</hi> which is there, is but another Deed of Confirmation, according to the mode of thoſe times, when, it was uſual to obtain ſuch, from ſeveral Princes, ſeveral Generations one after
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97674:39"/>another; and for proof hereof, I did deſire you to read <hi>Monaſticon Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canum,</hi> Par. 2 Pa. 24, and 25. where you might find King <hi>Henry</hi> the I. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing and confirming what had been given to the Priory of <hi>Huntendune,</hi> and pa. 27. how King <hi>Henry</hi> the III. did the like, and yet there was a greater ſpace betwixt King <hi>Henry</hi> the I. and King <hi>Henry</hi> the III. than there was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Randle de Gernoniis</hi> and <hi>Randle de Blundevil;</hi> and very many others of the like nature, may be found, by thoſe who will take the pains to make ſearch in the ſeveral <hi>Monaſticons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo, it is very ſtrange, that you ſhould fancy that the Roll, where the ſaid Deed in <hi>Monaſticon</hi> was written, ſhould be miſtaken both in <hi>Will.</hi> and <hi>R.</hi> eſpecially ſince the word <hi>Will.</hi> was the firſt word in the ſaid Deed; neither is it a badge of any miſtake in the ſaid Deed, becauſe the Archbiſhop of <hi>York</hi> is named in it, though the Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> (being at that time the ſame with the Biſhop of <hi>Coventry</hi> and <hi>Litch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi>) was not then ſubject to the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of <hi>York,</hi> but <hi>Canterbury;</hi> For,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97674:39"/>the Archbiſhop of <hi>York</hi> was not named upon that account, but, becauſe ſome of the places mentioned in the ſaid Deed, were within the Province and Dioceſſe of <hi>York,</hi> as particularly <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſington</hi> was, it being within the <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riding</hi> of <hi>Yorkſhire;</hi> but I ſuppoſe your principal reaſon why you ſuſpect the <hi>Roll</hi> was miſtaken is, becauſe you ſay, <hi>there was no ſuch Archbiſhop of</hi> York, <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> Will. <hi>nor Biſhop of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>whoſe Christian name began with</hi> R. <hi>both living at one time, either in the time of</hi> Randle Blundevill <hi>or</hi> Randle de Gernoniis, <hi>that you can find.</hi> Which ſaying of yours ſeems very ſtrange to me, but I believe all your doubt is about the <hi>Will.</hi> that was Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> becauſe Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> (a late Writer) in his <hi>Catalogue of Biſhops</hi> doth not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the ſaid <hi>Williams</hi> being choſen Archbiſhop immediately upon the death of <hi>Thurſtan;</hi> for I am conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that you are well ſatisfied that <hi>Roger Clinton</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> (as appears by the Third Part of the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſticon,</hi> page 218. as alſo by Biſhop <hi>Godwin, Jsaackson,</hi> Doctor <hi>Heylin, Sime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Dunelmenſis, Matt. Paris,</hi> and many
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97674:40"/>other antient Authors) from about 1128. until about the year 1148. or 1149. which fell out to be in the time of <hi>Randle de Gernoniis,</hi> for he was Earl, (as appears in your Book) from about the year 1128, till about the year 1153. And I doubt not but to make it as clear, that a <hi>William</hi> was Archbiſhop of <hi>York</hi> in the time of the ſaid <hi>Randle de Gernoniis</hi> and <hi>Roger Clinton,</hi> and though the ſaid <hi>William</hi> was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ouſted, yet whilſt he enjoyed that Archbiſhoprick, he was, and would in Deeds, and otherways, be owned as Archbiſhop of <hi>York;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that a <hi>William</hi> was Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> in the time of the ſaid <hi>Earl</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Biſhop,</hi> I have already ſhewed you in my former Book, out of <hi>Iſaackson's Chronology,</hi> and ſhall thus make it further to appear;</p>
            <p>If you look into Biſhop <hi>Godwin</hi>'s <hi>Catalogue</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> printed at <hi>London</hi> 1615, page 581. in the life of <hi>Heny Murdack,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> you may find him ſaying thus.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:97674:40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>King</hi> Stephen <hi>had a kinſman named</hi> William,
<note place="margin">1142. <hi>Stephen</hi> 8.</note> (<hi>that was Son unto</hi> Emma his Siſter, by Earl <hi>Herbert</hi>) a Man no leſs noble in Mind and Vertue, then Stock and Lineage. He being Treaſurer of <hi>York.</hi> was now elected unto the Archbiſhoprick, and having obtained Conſecration alſo, ſent to <hi>Rome</hi> for his Pall. His ſpeed there was not ſo good as he looked for; by ſome Adverſaries many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions were taken againſt him, whereby it came to paſs, not only his Suit was put off, and ſtayed for that time, but alſo Proceſs awarded to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh him to come thither in Perſon to anſwer the accuſations laid againſt him. At his coming to <hi>Rome,</hi> he found his Adverſaries many and Mighty. And among the reſt it is remembred, that St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> then living, was very earneſt againſt him. <hi>Eugenius</hi> the Pope, had been brought up in the Abbey of <hi>Clareual</hi> under <hi>St. Bernard,</hi> together with <hi>Henry Murdac,</hi> whom <hi>Williams</hi> adverſaries had ſet up to be a Suiter for his Archbiſhoprick. The Pope being thus carried away with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:97674:41"/>of his old Acquaintance, and ſome ſhew of matter, was content to deprive <hi>William,</hi> and to place <hi>Henry Murdac</hi> in his room, whom he cauſed to be Conſecrated preſently, and ſent him home into <hi>England</hi> with his Pall. King <hi>Stephen</hi> hearing this Newes, was much grieved with the diſgrace of his Nephew, which all Men judged unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. Therefore He ſtood upon Termes with the new Arch-biſhop, and required him to Swear unto Him fealty in ſome extraordinary manner; and when he denyed, eaſily took occaſion of diſpleaſure againſt him. The Townſmen of <hi>York</hi> that loved <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> exceedingly for his Gentleneſs and Vertuous behaviour amongſt them; hearing how the King was affected; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to receive <hi>Murdac</hi> into their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For this reſiſtance he ſuſpended them: which notwithſtanding, <hi>Euſtach</hi> the King's Son, commanded Service to be ſaid as at all other times was accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed. By means hereof, as alſo by reaſon that the King's Officers were very terrible and heavy enemies unto all that had laboured for the Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>William:</hi> Seditions and Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:97674:41"/>were daily raiſed in the City, amongſt which a certain Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, a Friend of the Archbiſhop, was ſlain. Two or three years theſe ſtirs continued, till at laſt, the Kings wrath (by means) being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed, <hi>York-men</hi> were content to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Archbiſhop peaceably. He governed very auſterely the ſpace of ten years, dyed <hi>Octob.</hi> 14. 1153. at <hi>Sherborne,</hi> and was buryed in his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral Church. And when <hi>Biſhop Godwin</hi> hath thus ſaid, he preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tells you, how the ſaid <hi>William</hi> (there called <hi>Saint William</hi>) after the death of <hi>Henry Murdac</hi> was again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to the ſaid Archbiſhoprick.</p>
            <p>Alſo, if you look in <hi>John Brompton</hi>'s Chronicon, <hi>col.</hi> 1028. <hi>l.</hi> 63. in the life of King <hi>Stephen,</hi> you may find him thus ſaying;</p>
            <q>Dicto autem <hi>Thurſtino Eboracenſi</hi> Archiepiſcopo Monaſterii <hi>Fontanenſis</hi> aliorumque octo fundatore, ut dictum eſt, decedente <hi>(and he dyed, ſayes the ſaid</hi> Brompton, col. <hi>1028:</hi> l. 25. <hi>in the year 1140. with which Biſhop Godwin doth
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:97674:42"/>accord)</hi> Singuli Eccleſiae Eboracenſis Canonici, beatum <hi>Willielmum</hi> ejuſdem Eccleſiae Theſaurarium praeferunt, tam pro honestate morum, quam excellentia meritorum. Iſte namque <hi>Willielmus</hi> ex ſpectabili proſapia Regis Stephani or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, praeclaris natalium titulis fuerat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignitus; erat enim ſilius potentiſſimi viri Comitis Herberti. Qui quamvis poſt deceſſum dicti Archiepiſcopi <hi>Thur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtani, ad ſedem Eboracenſem electus fuerat;</hi> invidia tamen &amp; impetuoſus amor dominandi quemdam ejuſdem Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae Archilevitam adeo in regionem diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudinis traxerant, ut inter eligentes diſcidium excitavit, ipſum <hi>Willielmum</hi> a ſaniori parte eïectum impediens licet de ejus electione clerus &amp; populus acclamaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent laudum praeconia, ſuſpenditur igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur cauſa ad Apoſtolicae ſedis examen pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocata.</q>
            <p>See alſo the ſaid <hi>Brompton</hi> to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Col.</hi> 1041. <hi>l.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Roger Hoveden</hi> who lived in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, King <hi>Richard</hi> the Firſt, and King <hi>John;</hi> in the Firſt Part of his <hi>Annalls,</hi> Printed
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:97674:42"/>at <hi>Frankfort</hi> 1601. <hi>Page</hi> 490. <hi>l.</hi> 51. writes thus of the Reſtitution of the ſaid <hi>William, eodem anno obiit</hi> Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus <hi>Eboracenſis Archiepiſcopus, quo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functo,</hi> Willielmus <hi>Archiepiſcopus, quem Papa</hi> Eugenius <hi>ſuſpenderat, Romam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus eſt, &amp; invenit gratiam apud</hi> Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſium <hi>Papam, &amp; redditus eſt ei Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiſcopatus Eboracenſis.</hi> And I think it is not to be doubted, though I have not yet found the place, but that the ſaid <hi>Hoveden</hi> doth ſpeak of his being choſen after the death of <hi>Thurſtan,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Iſaakſon</hi> in his <hi>Chronology,</hi> cites <hi>Hoveden</hi> for what he there ſayes, but he names not the Pages.</p>
            <p>Alſo, <hi>Thomas Stubbs</hi> (a Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can) writing of the Archbiſhops of <hi>York, col.</hi> 1721. <hi>l.</hi> 15. thus ſayes,</p>
            <q>Viceſſimus nonus ſucceſſit in Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopatum <hi>Eboracenſis</hi> eccleſiae <hi>Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Murdak</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſtercienſis ordinis Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus ae profeſſor probatiſſimus, vir mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae ſanctitatis &amp; abſtinentiae laudabilis. Defuncto namque, ut praemittitur, <hi>Thur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtino Eboracenſi</hi> Archiepiſcopo, convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catiſque ad electionem pontificis Canonicis eccleſiae <hi>Eboracenſis, Willielmus</hi> ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:97674:43"/>Eceleſiae Theſaurarius &amp; Canonicus exigentibus ſuis meritis a Majori &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niore parte in Archiepiſcopum eſt electus. Erat enim ſtrenuiſſimi Comitis <hi>Herberti</hi> filius ex <hi>Emma</hi> ſorore Regis <hi>Anglorum Stephani</hi> progenitus. Vir quidem gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re nobilis ſed morum excellentia &amp; vita mundiſſima incomparabiliter inſignis. Interea vero <hi>Osbertus</hi> archidiaconus <hi>Eboracenſis</hi> invidiae ſtimulo agitatus, facta inter eligentes diſſentione, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mationem ipſius electi licet ab omnibus dignus haberetur pertinaciter impedivit: ſuſpenſo igitur negotio partibuſque coram <hi>Romano</hi> pontifice ſuper hujus electionis diſcuſſione perſonditer vocatis, idem <hi>Willielmus</hi> perſequentibus illum adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſariis ſuis &amp; injuſte accuſantibus conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erationis gratiam minime potuit optimere. Lite ergo in curia <hi>Romana</hi> ſub Papa <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentio</hi> ſecundo, <hi>Celeſtino</hi> ſecundo, &amp; <hi>Lucio</hi> ſecundo per annos quinque &amp; am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius del ito proceſſu currente, nichil inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt quod ejus conſecrationem deberet elongare. Verum ſummus Paſtor <hi>Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Ciſtercienſis</hi> ordinis Monachus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Dominicae incarnationis <hi>M. C. xlvi.</hi> in Papam conſecratus electionem dicti <hi>Willielmi</hi> non ratione perſonalis inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habilitatis,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:97674:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>mmo pro libito ſuaevolunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis caſſavit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>And there he alſo after ſpeaks of the Reſtauration of the ſaid <hi>William</hi> to the ſaid Archbiſhoprick: ſo that it ſeems by this Author that the ſaid <hi>William</hi> held the ſaid Archbiſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prick upon his firſt election, till after the deaths of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, Pope <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the Second, and Pope <hi>Lucius</hi> the Second, <hi>viz.</hi> till about the year 1146. but was then ouſted by Pope <hi>Eugenius,</hi> and reſtored again by Pope <hi>Anaſtaſius,</hi> after the death of <hi>Henry Murdac</hi> about the year 1153.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Gulielmus Neubricenſis,</hi> who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Raignes of King <hi>Richard</hi> the Firſt, and King <hi>John, page</hi> 368. <hi>l.</hi> 10. thus writes,</p>
            <q>Venerabili Truſtino defuncto, Ebora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſis Eccleſiae Pontificatum ſuſcepit Guli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elmus ejusdem Eccleſiae Theſaurarius, vir plane ſecundum carnem nobilis, &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ingenua lenitate amabilis. Qui cum ad ſedem Apoſtolicam reſpenſales idoneos propetendo ſolemniter pallio di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rexiſſet: emergentibus adverſariis &amp; multa contra eum proponentibus negatum eſt. Juſſuſque ad eandem ſedem in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria perſona accedere &amp; pro ſemetipſo
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:97674:44"/>tanquam aetatem habens allegare: cauſis tamen ingraveſcentibus atque invaleſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus adverſariis, piae quoque memoriae Papa Eugenio contra eum, ſive per verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, ſive per ſurreptionem implacabiliter irritato depoſitus eſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>So alſo <hi>Gervaſius</hi> a Benedictine Monk of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who lived in the time of King <hi>John, Col.</hi> 1357. <hi>l.</hi> 52. in the year 1142. thus ſayes,</p>
            <q>Rex autem <hi>Stephanus</hi> dedit Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopatum <hi>Eboracenſis</hi> eccleſiae cuidem clerico nomine <hi>VVillielmo,</hi> quibuſdam clericis ejuſdem Eccleſiae conſentientibus, aliis vero ut audebant reclamantibus, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de factum eſt ut cum <hi>Theodbaldus Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuarienſis</hi> archiepiſcopus ſie factae non conſentiret electioni, <hi>Henricus</hi> frater Regis <hi>VVintonienſis</hi> epiſcopus apoſtolicae ſedis legatus, praeſumptuoſa ſemper mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimitate famam colligens, praedictum electum apud <hi>VVintoniam</hi> conſecraret. Abiit itaque novus ſacratus <hi>Eboracum,</hi> &amp; vix duobus annis ſedit in pace.</q>
            <p>Alſo, <hi>Radulſus de Diceto,</hi> who was Dean of <hi>Pauls,</hi> and lived in the time of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:97674:44"/>King <hi>John, Col.</hi> 508. <hi>l.</hi> 11. thus writes, <hi>Thurſtino Eboracenſi archiepiſcopo ſuc ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit</hi> Willielmus.</p>
            <p>Alſo, <hi>Matt. Paris</hi> (who lived in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third) in his <hi>Greater Hiſtory</hi> put out by Doctor <hi>Watts, Page</hi> 78. ſayes thus in the year 1139. Tune <hi>defuncto</hi> Turſtano <hi>Eboracenſi Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiſcopo,</hi> Willielmus <hi>ejuſdem Eccleſiae Theſaurarius ſucceſſit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo, <hi>Simeon Dunelmenſis,</hi> a Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictine Monk, who lived in the Raign of King <hi>Stephen,</hi> and in the time of the ſaid <hi>William, Col.</hi> 79. <hi>l.</hi> 39. ſpeaking of the Archbiſhops of <hi>York,</hi> thus ſayes; <hi>Poſt</hi> Oſwaldum <hi>iſti ſibi ordine ſucceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt,</hi> Aldulfus, Vulſtanus, Eelfricus, Kinſius, Aldredus, Thomas Girardus, Thomas, Turſtinus, Willielmus, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus, Rogerus; There placing the aforeſaid <hi>William</hi> before <hi>Henry Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dac.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>John Prior</hi> of <hi>Hagulstald,</hi> in his Continuation of the Hiſtory of the ſaid <hi>Simeon, Col.</hi> 268. <hi>l.</hi> 41. thus writes; <hi>Anno</hi> M.C. xlii. <hi>Poſt mortem</hi> Turſtini <hi>archiepiſcopi clerici</hi> Eboracen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <hi>ſecundum deſideria cordis ſui varia
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:97674:45"/>&amp; vaga ſententia circumacti fuerant to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to anno ſuper electione facienda. Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerant autem perſuadente legato</hi> Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co Wintoniae <hi>nepotem Regis</hi> Stephani Henricum <hi>de</hi> Coilli. <hi>Qui quia praefuit abbatiae</hi> Kadomenſi, <hi>noluit dominus apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicus eum praefici archiepiſcopatui niſi renunciaret priori honori. Menſe Janua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio iterum de electione tractantes, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonam</hi> Willielmi <hi>Theſaurarii plurimi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſerunt.</hi> And preſently after, <hi>l.</hi> 60. further ſayes, <hi>Perductum itaque electum ad</hi> Lincolniam <hi>rex libenter ſuſcepit, &amp; in terris &amp; poſſeſſionibus</hi> Eboracenſibus <hi>confirmavit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now though a leſſer number of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors might have ſerved to prove that there was a <hi>William</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> living in the time both of <hi>Randle de Gernoniis</hi> and <hi>Roger Clinton,</hi> yet I thought fit to cite all theſe, to let the world ſee that it was nothing elſe, which made you that you could not find it to be ſo, but becauſe you would not find it to be ſo; For, I know, you have moſt (if not all) of the ſaid Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, and if you would have made ſearch, you might eaſily have found what is here ſaid.</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:97674:45"/>
            <p>But beſides what is here alleadged, if you had but obſerved thoſe Deeds of <hi>Richard Bacun</hi> and <hi>Randle Blundevil</hi> which are mentioned <hi>Monaſticon An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicanum, Part</hi> 2. <hi>Page</hi> 267 <hi>&amp;</hi> 268. and the Deeds of <hi>Randle de Gernoniis</hi> that are in your own <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities,</hi> you would eaſily have known that the ſaid <hi>Richard Bacun</hi> did live in the time of the ſaid <hi>Randle de Gernoniis;</hi> For to the ſaid Deed of <hi>Richard Bacun, Hugo Wac, Willielmus</hi> Conſtabularius de <hi>Donington, Thurſtanus Banaſtre, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmus Bacoun, Robertus Bacoun, Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elmus de Colevile, Richardus Pincerna, Willielmus de Binulle, Galfridus Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarius, Willielmus Capellanus,</hi> and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes Capellanus</hi> are Witneſſes: and to the ſaid Deed of <hi>Randle Blundevil, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerus Conſtabularius Ceſtriae, Rogerus de Montealto Seneſchallus Ceſtriae, Simon de Kyma, Thomas Diſpenſarius, Simon de Thochet, Willielmus de Hardreſhulle, Hugo de Nevilla, Henricus de Longo Campo, Philippus de Horreby, Sampſon Prior de Trentham,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Clericus</hi> are wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</p>
            <p>Now as it would appear probable
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:97674:46"/>(if there were nothing elſe in the caſe) that this Deed of <hi>Richard Bacun</hi> was not made in the time of <hi>Randle Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devil,</hi> becauſe there is not any one perſon a witneſs to the ſaid Deed of <hi>Richard Bacun,</hi> who was a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the ſaid Deed of <hi>Randle Blundevil</hi> (or to any other Deed of his, that I can find) So it certainly appears from your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities,</hi> that thoſe who were witneſſes to <hi>Richard Bacuns</hi> ſaid Deed, did live in the time of Earl <hi>Randle de Gernoniis,</hi> and not in the time of <hi>Randle Blundevil;</hi> For, as you may there ſee, <hi>Page</hi> 126 <hi>&amp;</hi> 127. in the Deed made by <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy,</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Randle de Gernoniis,</hi> the aforeſaid <hi>Hugh Wac,</hi> and <hi>Richard Pincerna</hi> were then witneſſes on the behalf of the ſaid <hi>Randle,</hi> alſo <hi>Page</hi> 128. to one Deed of the ſaid <hi>Randle,</hi> the ſaid <hi>William Colevile</hi> was a witneſs, and to another of the ſaid <hi>Randle</hi>'s Deeds the ſaid <hi>Willielmus Capellanus</hi> and <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chardus Pincerna</hi> were witneſſes, and <hi>Page</hi> 160 <hi>&amp;</hi> 161. to another Deed of the ſaid <hi>Randle de Gernoniis</hi> the ſaid <hi>Thurſtan Banaſter, Richard Pincerna,</hi> and <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Chaplain</hi> were witneſſes;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:97674:46"/>and ſo alſo the ſaid <hi>Richard Pincerna, Thurſtanus Banaſter,</hi> and <hi>Willielmus Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellanus</hi> were witneſſes to another Deed of the ſaid <hi>Randle de Gernoniis</hi> concerning <hi>Neither-Whitley,</hi> mentioned by you, <hi>Page</hi> 387. Though you there run upon a miſtake, and ſay that <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Blundevil</hi> made that Deed, which cannot be, Becauſe thoſe witneſſes (as appears before) did live in the time of <hi>Randle de Gernoniis,</hi> and not in the time of the ſaid <hi>Randle Blundevil,</hi> they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no witneſſes at any time to any Deed of <hi>Randle Blundevils</hi> that I can find, although he was Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> above fifty years, ſo that nothing can poſſibly be more clear than this is.</p>
            <p>As to the word <hi>aſperſed</hi> which you fault me for uſing, I do not apprehend that it ſignifies <hi>a malicious ſeeking to throw dirt in anothers face unjuſtly;</hi> For, to aſperſe, properly ſignifies but to <hi>beſprinkle,</hi> with which, malice will ſeldom reſt ſatisfied: and I will do you this right, to declare that I believe it is not malice, but a deſire to divulge your ſuppoſed new Diſcovery, which occaſioned you thus to do.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:97674:47"/>
            <p>That way of Arguing which you uſe in the 57 <hi>Page</hi> is very odd; For, Becauſe you ſuppoſe the <hi>Reſpondent</hi> will deny your <hi>Minor,</hi> you would have him give over anſwering, and turn <hi>Opponent,</hi> and ſo endeavour to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove what you ought to prove; But what you ſay, <hi>Page</hi> 58. that you have proved <hi>Amicia to be a Baſtard, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Hugh Cyveliok had a former Wife,</hi> and alſo <hi>Page</hi> 59. <hi>that if he had no other Wife but</hi> Bertred, <hi>and ſhe no Daughter to</hi> Bertred, <hi>then certainly if ſhe be a Daughter and ſo called, ſhe muſt needs be a Baſtard,</hi> is undoubtedly true; For <hi>Amicia</hi> muſt needs be a <hi>baſtard,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſhe was <hi>legitimate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You grant in your 59 <hi>
                  <hi>Page,</hi> That my proving</hi> Amicia <hi>to be called a daughter ſo long ſince, ſhe ought to be preſumed legitimate, till the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary appear;</hi> But why therefore do not you preſume her ſo to be? And though you pretend there are many ſtrong reaſons to the contrary, yet I have ſhewed the invalidity of them all, and therefore what I have formerly
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:97674:47"/>ſaid ſtands good, and is to the point, <hi>viz.</hi> That the proving that ſhe was not by <hi>Bertred,</hi> does not prove that ſhe was a baſtard, but onely proves that ſhe was either a baſtard, or by a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer wife.</p>
            <p>And as to what you alleadg, <hi>Page</hi> 60. that, <hi>though the Law allowes not this in pleadings, what hinders but Baſtardy may be proved by Hiſtory or Argumentation af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the parties death? As, ſupppoſe in a Register-Book you find ſuch a Baſtard Chriſtened one hundred yeares ago, may not you justly call that perſon a bastard, whom you find ſo Registred?</hi> I do an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer and ſay, That even in that caſe, though it be good proof, that there was then a Baſtard of that name, yet if in any Deed (or otherwayes) in the ſame Age you find one of that name, you are not to be too poſitive that that Man was that Baſtard, becauſe, there might be more perſons than one of the ſame Name, whoſe Fathers might alſo be of the ſame Name each with other; and though theſe miſtakes might eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be cleared by the party concerned whilſt he was alive, yet it may be dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:97674:48"/>ſometimes to do it after he is dead: And that is (as I ſuppoſe) one reaſon why the Law gives no liberty to prove Baſtardy againſt any Man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death. But the caſes of the children of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt</hi> by <hi>Katherine Swynford</hi> are not like to this caſe, For you certainly know that they were born Baſtards, but afterwards legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated; and I think, after their legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, they might have had the ſame remedies againſt any that did call them Baſtards, that perſons lawfully born might have.</p>
            <p>Whereas I tell you out of Sir <hi>Henry Spelman,</hi> that in caſes of honor and profit (by the cuſtomes of <hi>Normandy) appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione filiorum non comprehenduntur ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardi;</hi> You anſwer and ſay; <hi>that in other caſes, and formerly by the appellation of ſons, baſtards were comprehended,</hi> and <hi>that this makes directly againſt me;</hi> But how this makes againſt me, in what caſes ſoever baſtards were formerly compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by the appellation of Sons and Daughters, if they were not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in caſes of <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>profit,</hi> I cannot tell, feeing that <hi>Amicia</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:97674:48"/>a Daughter, and that in a caſe of ſo great <hi>profit,</hi> that you will needs have it to be her whole Portion.</p>
            <p>And whereas you mention the next words of <hi>Spelman,</hi> viz. that <hi>the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Northern people admitted baſtards to ſucceed in their inheritance; and that</hi> William <hi>the Conquerour was not aſhamed of that title, who began his Letter to</hi> Alan <hi>Earl of</hi> Little-Britaine <hi>as he did many others, Ego</hi> Willielmus <hi>cognomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Baſtardus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not know how you can apply thoſe expreſſions to the caſe in hand, and if you could, they would make againſt you; For, when Baſtard chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were ſo much eſteemed, as to be admitted to ſucceed in the inheritance, then certainly illegitimate Daughters would have great Portions as well as thoſe that were legitimate, And why ſhould not <hi>Amicia,</hi> if ſhe was a Baſtard, be ſo called, as well as <hi>Paganus</hi> was? (who, as you ſay, was the Son of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi>) Or why ſhould <hi>Hugh Cyve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liok</hi> himſelf, be more aſhamed to call her ſo, than <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conqueror</hi> was to ſtile himſelf a Baſtard:</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:97674:49"/>
            <p>What elſe you have ſaid, <hi>Page</hi> 61, 62 <hi>&amp;</hi> 63. hath been ſaid over and over again by you, and hath formerly received a full Anſwer.</p>
            <p>In the 64 <hi>&amp;</hi> 65 <hi>Pages</hi> you recite and endeavour to fortifie an Argument of mine, which I brought not as a good Argument, but compared it to one of yours, to ſhew the invalidity thereof; neither did I at all doubt, but that <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam, Randle</hi> and <hi>Wydo</hi> (Sons of the aforeſaid <hi>Roger Mainwaring</hi>) were all legitimate, it being good proof there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that in ſo antient a Record, they are all three called <hi>Sons</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger;</hi> But I ſhewed you by the Rule by which you went <hi>viz.</hi> that none ſhould be believed lawfull, unleſs we could directly and in <hi>terminis</hi> prove their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to be married, that the ſaid <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, Randle,</hi> and <hi>Wido,</hi> and moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that lived in the Firſt and Second Centuries might be concluded to be Baſtards; And though you tell me, <hi>that I here argue well</hi> (which muſt needs be, becauſe this Argument of mine is ſo like to yours) <hi>and that you would ſay to
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:97674:49"/>my Minor, that</hi> Roger <hi>had a Wife though we yet know not who ſhe was; and that this appears certainly, becauſe the Lands deſcended from heir to heir,</hi> and that you tell me, how you would <hi>frame your affirmative part more formally;</hi> Yet in ſtead of trying whether you could in <hi>terminis</hi> prove (which by this your Rule you ought to do) whether <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> who was the eldeſt of the three Sons of the ſaid <hi>Roger,</hi> was his lawful Son, or but a baſtard, you beg what you ſhould prove, and take it for granted that he was the Son and Heir, and ſay, <hi>that if the Son and Heir of</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <hi>ſucceeded by deſcent in his Fathers Inheritance, then</hi> Roger <hi>had a Wiſe;</hi> whereas if <hi>William</hi> was the Son and Heir of <hi>Roger,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Roger</hi> his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt needs have a Wife, whether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever <hi>William</hi> ſucceeded in the Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance by deſcent, or was diſinheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; For, none but a lawful Son, can be a Son and Heir; and the ſame que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion you beg, when you pretend (<hi>p.</hi> 65.) to prove the ſequel of your Major. For in that Argument you ſay, <hi>Ergo, if the Son and Heir of</hi> Roger <hi>ſucceeded by deſcent in the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:97674:50"/>then</hi> Roger <hi>muſt needs have a Wife, and nothing appears here of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>al ſettlement;</hi> But beſides you begging of the Queſtion, the only reaſon which you bring to prove the ſaid <hi>William</hi> did ſucceed by deſcent (and by conſequence that his Father was Marryed) is, <hi>betauſe, nothing appears here of a ſpecial ſettlement;</hi> But this is not a proving certainly and in <hi>terminis</hi> that the ſaid <hi>Roger</hi> had a Wife, for though no ſpecial ſettlement doth appear yet, if we muſt be tyed to this your way of proving, <hi>William</hi> might poſſibly be a Baſtard, and might come in by ſpecial ſettlement, though the ſaid ſettlement be now loſt; So that this retorted Argument is but weakly anſwered.</p>
            <p>What you ſay, <hi>Page</hi> 66, 67, 68 <hi>&amp;</hi> 69, is but what you have formerly ſaid and I have abundantly anſwered, and your alleadging <hi>that</hi> Amicia <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the firſt venter, is therefore more worthy than thoſe of the ſecond,</hi> is ſufficiently confuted by thoſe words of mine, which you repeat in your 70 <hi>Page;</hi> For though it be true that if a
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:97674:50"/>Man die, and leave only Daughters, which are by ſeveral Wives, that thoſe of the firſt venter, ſhall be more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy than thoſe of the ſecond, yet if a Brother dye (as in this caſe) and have no iſſue of his own, nor any Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but only leave Siſters, which were by two ſeveral venters, if that Brother was of the ſecond venter, (as <hi>Randle Blundevile</hi> was) then thoſe Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that were of the ſecond venter, ſhall be preferred before thoſe of the firſt, Becauſe, thoſe were of the whole blood to their Brother, whereas the Siſters by the firſt venter were but of the half blood.</p>
            <p>What you alleadge, <hi>Page</hi> 71, 72 <hi>&amp;</hi> 73, doth not prove that Earl <hi>Hugh</hi>'s Grant, was a Releaſe of the Service of one Knights-Fee; But that, and all the reſt in thoſe <hi>Pages</hi> (as you truly ſay) being nothing to the argument in hand, I will not trouble my ſelf or the Reader therewith: Only let me ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeve, that there is no probability at all, but that Sir <hi>Raph Mainwaring</hi> had a farr greater Portion with his VVife than thoſe Services; For, the having
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:97674:51"/>the ſervice of three Knights-Fees, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſervice of two Knights-fees, was in effect the having the ſervice but of one Knights-Fee, and as I told you in my former Book, was not a Portion ſuitable to the Eſtate of a very mean Gentleman; ſo that it was certainly a free-gift of the ſaid <hi>Earl,</hi> after the ſaid Marriage was paſt and conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated; And that Grant to him is ſo far from proving, that he had no greater Portion, that you your ſelf, when you are told, 'tis like he had a great deal more, do confeſs (<hi>Page</hi> 71.) <hi>it may be ſo, What then?</hi> And if it be ſo, that he had a greater Portion, and it doth not appear how much that Portion was, you can raiſe no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from thence, ſo that this your ſecond Reaſon is very invalid.</p>
            <p>Alſo it is very probable that the Lordſhip of <hi>Henbury</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> might be part of the Portion of the ſaid <hi>Amicia;</hi> For as appears in your <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Antiquities, Page</hi> 107. <hi>Henbury</hi> was one of thoſe Towns which <hi>Hugh Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> held in Demaine, And I do not find that any <hi>Mainwaring</hi> was poſſeſſed thereof, before Sir <hi>Raph Mainwaring,</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:97674:51"/>who was Husband to the ſaid <hi>Amicia</hi> neither have I ever yet ſeen or heard of any Record or Deed which ſhews how <hi>Henbury</hi> firſt came to the <hi>Mainwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas you tell me, (<hi>Page</hi> 74, when you ſpeak of your Third and laſt Reaſon) that I might have done well to have anſwered your firſt Reaſon better; I ſhall appeale to the Reader, whether your Third Reaſon, which you your ſelf confeſs not to be evincing, be not as ſtrong as your firſt, and upon the matter the ſame with it; as alſo, whether I have not given both your firſt and third Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons a very full anſwer, in the 62, 63, 66 <hi>&amp;</hi> 67 <hi>Pages</hi> of my former Book, and therefore it will not be taken off with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out better reaſon given by you, then your bare denying it to be a ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Anſwer; So that all your three Reaſons againſt <hi>Amicia,</hi> are of no weight at all.</p>
            <p>Alſo, what I have there ſaid will give full ſatisfaction to the Queſtion you did pleaſe to ask, <hi>viz. Whether I
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:97674:52"/>find that the Hiſtorians have left out any of Earl</hi> Hughes <hi>legitimate Children, except this whom I ſuppoſe to be legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate?</hi> For, thoſe Hiſtorians only ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king upon them to Record who were heires to <hi>Randle Blundevil;</hi> If <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> had had never ſo many Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by his former Wife, they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have taken notice of any of them.</p>
            <p>And whereas you obſerve, <hi>Page</hi> 75. How I ſay, that Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> hath mentioned <hi>Amicia,</hi> though not among the Coheires, yet without the brand of a Baſtard, and do reply, <hi>that I know well that he is but of late ſtanding, and not an Hiſtorian contemporary with</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micia, <hi>and that you and I do alſo menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her.</hi> It is very ſtrange that you ſhould thus ſay, whereas the only rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why I did ſpeak of Mr. <hi>Cambden,</hi> was, becauſe, you had ſaid, <hi>That he was one of thoſe Hiſtorians who had taken no notice of the ſaid</hi> Amicia, and I onely named him to ſhew you your miſtake therein.</p>
            <p>The reſt which you ſay in the 75 <hi>&amp;</hi> 76 <hi>Pages,</hi> is but what you have
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:97674:52"/>formerly ſaid, and hath received an anſwer before.</p>
            <p>In your 77, 78 <hi>&amp;</hi> 79 <hi>Pages,</hi> you are alſo ſo far from anſwering that Argument of mine, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained between the 69 <hi>&amp;</hi> 75 <hi>Pages</hi> of my former Book, that that which you pretend to be an Anſwer (if rightly underſtood) is the very Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument which I there frame againſt you; For, though what you ſay, <hi>Page</hi> 78. be true, that ſometimes the <hi>Juſtice</hi> is put after the <hi>Conſtable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer,</hi> and ſometimes before the <hi>Conſtable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer,</hi> yet all the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> except Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> are named in the Charts of the Earles of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Conſtable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer,</hi> and are alſo named after the <hi>Conſtable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer,</hi> when they were witneſſes to any Deeds; But it is only in the time of the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> when the <hi>Juſtice</hi> is named before the <hi>Conſtable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer,</hi> in the Charts of the ſaid Earles, and it is only he who is named as a witneſs, and that frequently before the <hi>Conſtable</hi> and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:97674:53"/>
               <hi>Dapifer,</hi> as I have proved by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Deeds, which I then mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both out of your former Book, and elſewhere, and doth alſo fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appear by another Deed in your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities, Page</hi> 205. where the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> is alſo named as a Witneſs before the then <hi>Dapifer, Ralph de Montealto;</hi> And this reſpect was ſhewed to the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> although, as you may ſee in your ſaid Book, <hi>Page</hi> 160 <hi>&amp;</hi> 161. that the Conſtable by Charter was to go next the <hi>Earl,</hi> and had his office in Fee, and that the Steward was to go next af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Conſtable, and had his Office alſo in Fee; But when <hi>Philip Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby,</hi> who did ſucceed the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> was Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> then, according to the old uſual way, as appeares in the 162. <hi>Page</hi> of your Firſt Book, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable and Dapifer were again named in the Earles Chart before the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and alſo as you may ſee at the bottom of the 144 <hi>Page,</hi> and the top of the 145 <hi>Page</hi> of your ſaid Book, the ſaid Conſtable was
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:97674:53"/>named as a Witneſs before <hi>Philip de Orreby,</hi> though then Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter;</hi> And I believe you cannot ſhew any Chart of any of the Earles of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> in which any other Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter</hi> had the like preeminence; neither do I think you can ſhew any Deeds in which any other Juſtice is named as a Witneſs before the Conſtable or Dapifer, and if any ſuch ſingle pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent can perchance be found, I am confident it will prove to be a Deed wherein the ſaid <hi>Philip de Orreby</hi> is named as a Witneſs, and was occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by the ſimplicity of the Clark, who did write the ſaid Deed, who finding Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter</hi> (the immediate Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of the ſaid <hi>Philip de Orreby</hi>) to be written as a Witneſs before the Conſtable and Dapifer, might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon think that <hi>Philip de Orreby</hi> ſhould alſo be ſo placed; But it appeares by the aforeſaid proofes, and by ſeveral other Deeds, that it was not allowed to the ſaid <hi>Philip;</hi> And although you truly object, in the 78 <hi>Page, How great the uncertainty of ſubſcription of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:97674:54"/>Witneſſes was in old Deeds, ſometimes putting one before another in one Deed, and after putting the ſame perſon after the other in another Deed;</hi> yet, that will be nothing in this caſe; for, you your ſelf confeſs, <hi>Page</hi> 160 <hi>&amp;</hi> 161. of your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities;</hi> notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>uncertainty of ſubſcription of Witneſſes, that after certain Offices were annexed to certain Barons, that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was without controverſie</hi> (as to the Conſtable and Dapifer) <hi>and that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable of</hi> Cheſhire <hi>in Fee carried it clear by his Office,</hi> which was <hi>annexed to his Barony, and that the Steward</hi> was the <hi>next after him;</hi> And therefore this preeminence being thus given to the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph,</hi> and to him onely; and he alſo, ſo farr as I have found, being ever named before all the other Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons of <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> after he had Married the ſaid <hi>Amicia,</hi> as well when he had parted with his Office of Juſtice, as before; I think I may ſtill ſay, it will be difficult to give a Reaſon thereof, if he did not Marry a <hi>lawful</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the aforeſaid <hi>Earl.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:97674:54"/>
            <p>I have now done, but cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr with you, that the Honour of our Grandmother (the Mother of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micia</hi>) is a <hi>trivial thing;</hi> However, I am glad to Read, That you take your leave for ever of this Controverſie, becauſe I hope all occaſion of future Conteſt will be thereby taken away betwixt You and Him who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Affectionate Kinſman and very humble Servant Thomas Mainwaring.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Baddeley,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt</hi> 5 1673.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
